<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The creples complaint, or, A sermon preached Sept. 29, 1661 at Akly, near Buckingham, upon some sad occasion in which among many motives unto loyalty and other religious duties is proved, by lamentable experience, that good things are better known when they are not, than when they are enjoyed / by Thomas Philpot.</title>
            <author>Philpot, Thomas, b. 1588?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54805</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2124A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28438</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10594720</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10594720</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45328</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54805)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45328)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1408:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The creples complaint, or, A sermon preached Sept. 29, 1661 at Akly, near Buckingham, upon some sad occasion in which among many motives unto loyalty and other religious duties is proved, by lamentable experience, that good things are better known when they are not, than when they are enjoyed / by Thomas Philpot.</title>
                  <author>Philpot, Thomas, b. 1588?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 45 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Leake,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John V, 7 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title">
            <pb facs="tcp:45328:1"/>
            <p>THE CREPLES Complaint: Or, A SERMON Preached <hi>Sept.</hi> 29. 1661.</p>
            <p>At <hi>AKLY</hi> near <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CKING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HAM,</hi> upon ſome ſad OCCASION.</p>
            <p>In which, among many Motives unto LOYALTY And other Religious DUTIES, is proved, by lamentable Experience, <hi>That good things are better known when they are not, than when they are enjoyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS PHILPOT,</hi> D.D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Leake,</hi> at the Crown in <hi>Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet,</hi> between the two Temple Gates. 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45328:2"/>
            <head>To him that readeth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ould I addreſs my weak endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours unto any one, it ſhould be to Him who is moſt worthy to wear the Diadem, and is moſt willing to relieve all thoſe that are diſtreſſed, but — <hi>Haud equidem tali me dignor honore,</hi> ſuch honour is too high for my humility. Shall His Highneſs but be pleaſed to caſt a favourable eye on this poor Creple as he paſſeth, I ſhall ſay with aged <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, It is enough,</hi> for then I ſhall ſee one happy day again before I dye.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>READER adieu.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <opener>
               <date>Junii <hi>27. 1662.</hi>
               </date>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRIMATUR,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Robertus Pory S. T. P. Reverend. in Chriſto Patriac Domino Domino Archiepiſcopo Cantuar. Sacella.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45328:2"/>
            <head>The CREPLES Complaint.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>John 5.7.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>I have no man to help me.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Apelles</hi> was appointed by <hi>Alexander</hi> to take the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the fair Campaſpe a captive Lady, he was ſo in love with her beauty, that his affection maſtering his fancy, when he went to work could make nothing of it. In like manner many rare Aſtiſts intending to make a Mappe, as it were, of Gods mercies, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt it unto the world. Did ſo much admire the matter, that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got the form: Finding alſo by <hi>Davids</hi> many hundred hills and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of mountains ſo often mentioned, that there were Lands not yet diſcovered, which might in time be found, did alſo imagine that there might be an <hi>America</hi> of Gods mercies, or a greater part of them yet unknown which in their Coſmography they could not yet find, and ſo forſook the work, all crying out, <hi>This knowledge is too wonderful for us, we cannot attain unto it.</hi> And well might they ſay ſo, for Gods mercies being above all his works, where ſhould we find or know the ſumme of them, unleſſe we ſhould ſeek beyond the — <hi>Primum Mobile,</hi> where our brains would find a <hi>Vacuum.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore omitting his merciful Providence and preordination before the Creation, let us with modeſty ſpeak of his mercy ſince the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on until now. Firſt, the whole earth is but a Salviary or Phyſick gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, in which are as many Salutary Simples as there are ſeveral Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures under the Sunne, and as ſome ſuppoſe, not one more or leſſe, and that there may be as many Confections made out of them as ſhould cure all hurts, diſeaſes or diſaſters incident unto them whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. And as a Spider or a Bee hath found out more vertue in each Vegitable than <hi>Solomons</hi> univerſal Herbal ever heard of. So there is not a Butterfly, or the leaſt of any Flyes but hath found out ſome O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piated quality in each flower whereby they may take their reſt and ſleep all thoſe eight months in which R. is in, and when R. is out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to fly about again. And hath God ſuch care for his Diſcecta or deſpicable creatures as we ſuppoſe them, and hath he not more care for us? O let us not be of ſo little faith, for you ſhall hear what he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45328:3"/>hath done for our ſouls. Firſt, no ſooner was there a Serpent that cauſed man to break the Ordinance of God, but there was a man ordained to break the Serpents head for the breach thereof. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, no ſooner an <hi>Adam</hi> by whoſe diſobedience came death, but there was an <hi>Adam</hi> by whoſe obedience came the reſurrection from the dead. Thirdly, no ſooner an <hi>Eva</hi> betraying an <hi>Adam,</hi> who caus'd us all to be accurſed, but there was an <hi>Ave</hi> the cauſe of bearing an <hi>Adam</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by again we all are bleſſed. Fourthly, no ſooner a garden in which <hi>Adam</hi> firſt offended, but there was a garden in which to expiate the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence Chriſt muſt be apprehended. Fifthly, as in the garden there was a green tree by which Satans Kingdom was enriched, ſo near a garden there was a dead tree by which his Kingdom was impoveriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for ſo at Chriſts deſcention the confuſed company all confeſſed, crying — <hi>Per lignum ditamur, per lignum evertimur.</hi> The tree by which man died enriched our ſtore, the tree on which Chriſt died hath made us poor. Laſt of all, as by the fruit in the womb all our teeth were ſet on edge; ſo by the fruit of the womb that ſaying never ſhall be ſaid again. But neerer home, the manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods mercies hath been moſt eminent among us, though not deſerving the leaſt of them. Firſt, when this Nation was an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when our <hi>Goſhen</hi> was a <hi>Golgotha,</hi> when our <hi>Canaan</hi> was an <hi>Achel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dama.</hi> Secondly, when the Roſes of this Relm, White and Red, were not only blaſted in the Bud, their Stemme being cut off, but Bud and Bloſſome, root and branch were to be rooted up. When the houſe of <hi>Danchaſter</hi> never ſo illuſtrious by a judicious and ingenuous <hi>Joſiah</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Char. II.</note> the joy of the Church, the incourager of the Clergy, the reviver of Religion was almoſt loſt, when the houſe of <hi>York,</hi> never more glorious than by an high deſerving and undaunted <hi>Dedan</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">D. York.</note> the cheriſher of Chivalry, the gallantry of the Gantlet was quite forgot. Thirdly, when the Lily<note n="*" place="margin">The Church.</note> of this Land, formerly, as rich as <hi>Solomon</hi> in all his royalty, taking her ſweet repoſe among the Roſes, was now the Lily in the <hi>Canticles</hi> indeed among the thorns, who with the Nitingale— <hi>Spinis cincta canit,</hi> being compaſſed about with calamity, did not dare to tune her notes but in the night, being alſo in the ſame condition as was <hi>Abrahams</hi> Lamb in the bryars ready for a Sacrifice. Laſt of all, when our <hi>Iſrael</hi> had been twenty years vexed very ſore by <hi>Jabin</hi> and <hi>Siſſera,</hi> when in this condition they cryed unto God, being deſtitute of all help, as this poor Creple was, who had no man to help him; Then God in his me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cy ſent a bleſſed <hi>Barak</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">D. Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marle.</note>, a light from heaven, as the word will bear it, to give light again unto our <hi>Goſhen,</hi> where for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45328:3"/>want of it the people ſate in darkneſſe, and in the ſhadow of death. He alſo in his mercy ſent a diſcreet <hi>Deborah</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Madam Jane Lane.</note>, an induſtrious Bee as St. <hi>Jerom</hi> will have her, to bring ſweet honey again into our <hi>Cannan,</hi> where before there was nothing but Gall and Vinegar to drink. And now as this poor Creple had no help but what came from heaven, ſo but for theſe helpers each of us might ſtill have lain languiſhing, and cryed, <hi>I have no man to help me.</hi> In the three following points, obſerve,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Who this Creple was, an</hi> individuum vagum, <hi>a diſeaſed man.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>How cured, by Chriſt, all other Phyſitians having for ſaken him.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Why no ſooner cured?</hi> Becauſe he had no man to help him.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Diſeaſes as they are divers, ſo are they dangerous, eſpecially thoſe that are diurnal or diuturnal. Firſt, diurnal, ſuch as Hectick-Fevers, who keeping daily their conſtant courſe, &amp; uſual hours, and as they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or at an hour. So ſometime they happen in an hour and are not holpen in a year. Secondly, diuturnal, ſuch as Sciaticaes, who like wantons, feed upon Jellies got betwixt the joynts, and will not willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly change their diet, not eaſily be ejected; for ſo the Poet — <hi>Sero medicina paratur— Cum mala per longas convaluere moras,</hi> though that is not loſt which comes at laſt, yet that is loſt which comes too late. <hi>Hipocrates</hi> doth ſecond the Poet, ſaying— <hi>Morbi ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſcentes medendi ſunt difficiles</hi>— Diſeaſes durable, are hardly curable. In all which diſeaſes, as the <hi>Criſis,</hi> ſo the <hi>Creſis</hi> is to be conſidered; which <hi>Criſis</hi> is not the day when one doth feele himſelf ſick, but when he doth— <hi>Succumbere morbo,</hi> find that he is ſick, by reaſon that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe had gotten the dominion over him. Secondly, the <hi>Criſis</hi> is not when— <hi>Conſuetudi tollit ſenſum,</hi> when cuſtome taketh away the ſence of feeling of what is ſuffered, but when cuſtome being a ſecond nature— <hi>Expellas furca licet,</hi> will not eaſily be repulſed, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by this poor man who had been diſeaſed eight and thirty years, and could not be cured but by a miracle. And now as theſe habitual diſeaſes are in diſtempered bodies, ſo are they alſo in diſaffected diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, eſpecially in ſuch claudicants or lame Lourdans, who when they are moſt diſeaſed, have leaſt care to be cured. Firſt, ſuch are— <hi>Claudicantes in officio,</hi> lame in their duties, or in their offices; and although I intend not to meddle with Officers either in Court or Countrey, yet I hope it will be no ill office to tell them what Officers there are. There are firſt <hi>Oſtiarii,</hi> ſuch door-keepers as <hi>David</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to be one, which was, to be a doot-keeper in the houſe of God, and he had good reaſon for to deſire it, for then he ſhould be more ſure to be Porter of Heaven-gate, than St. <hi>Peter;</hi> for, — <hi>Domus
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45328:4"/>Dei eſt Porta Coeli: The houſe of God is the gate of Heaven.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Oſtiaerii,</hi> not that their doors are braſs, but that the Door-keepers do deſire — <hi>Aes alienum numerare,</hi> to have ſome of the money at the door to be their own, and if not, ſhould Chriſt himſelf ſtand at the door and knock, the Door-keepers will have ears, but will not hear; hands, but not as much as heave up a latch, unleſſe they may handle what they would have. Thirdly, there are—<hi>Pſeudothyra,</hi> back-doors, with this inſcription—<hi>Poſtico falle clientem,</hi> if thou ſeeſt nothing coming to thee at the fore-door, get thee out at the back-door, and let thy Client knock till he be weary. Fourthly, <hi>Feo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dothyra</hi> ſuch doors as <hi>Aeneas</hi> could not have opened unto him until he had given <hi>Cerberus</hi> a ſop, but ſuch door-keepers ſhould be wary in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving ſuch ſops, knowing who it was, that entred into <hi>Iſcariot</hi> ſo ſoone as the ſop was received. Fifthly, —<hi>Bifores valva</hi>—Two-leafed doors which are ſaid to move—<hi>Argenti limine</hi> — hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on ſilver hooks, ſhutting alſo, and opening on ſilver threſholds; ſuch doors hang heavie on the hinges, and if they be not well oyled, the Door-keepers will out of their affected ignorance miſtake the meaning of their honeſt Maſters, for when this is their rule—</p>
            <q>Porta patens esto, nulli clauderis honeſto.</q>
            <p>Let your door be open to all Petitioners, eſpecially to honeſt men. The Door-keepers miſtaking the <hi>comma</hi> or <hi>point,</hi> make alſo a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſtruction, and write it thus — <hi>Porta patens esto nulli, clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deris henesto.</hi> Let not your door be opened unto any Petitioner— <hi>Salvo feodo,</hi> eſpecially to an honeſt man. So that the feeling of a Pulſe may be as proper to a Porter as to a Phyſitian. There are other— Claudicants which are not Officers, and yet are lame in their offices and duties in a higher degree, and that is in coming to Church to ſerve God; and ſuch are they who cannot keep the Sabbath without break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sabbath, for when on that day our ſervants and our cattle ſhould reſt from all ſervile labour as well as our ſelves, and when the ſeventh day is a feaſt as well as a reſt, yet on that day they muſt faſt and not reſt, and all to eaſe the lameneſſe, or rather lazineſſe of thoſe who when they come to Church — <hi>Spectatum veniunt, veniunt ſpectentur ut ipſae.</hi> Come neither to hear nor to learn, but to ſee and to be ſeen. And what ſhall we ſee, Reeds ſhaking and waving with every wind? Or what ſhall we ſee, Males and Females,— <hi>In mollicie carnis,</hi> cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſoft rayment? But what ſhall we ſee, a company of <hi>Jacobs</hi> party-coloured Kids or ſpotted Lambs? Yea, we ſhall ſee many of your fine
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45328:4"/>
               <hi>Rufilli,</hi> who but for their— <hi>Pastilli</hi> and powders would be <hi>Gorgonii.</hi> The Poet doth ſpeak it plainer—<hi>Paſtillos Rufillus olet Gorgonius hireum.</hi>— That is, as al the ill-ſented skins of thoſe Kids which <hi>Jacob</hi> had upon his hands and the ſmooth of his neck would have been offenſive to his father, but for the cloths of his brother, whoſe ſmell was as the ſweet ſmell of a field which the Lord had bleſſed. So all their—Eſſences as they terme them, and other effeminate Odors would be ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive unto God that he would not endure them, were it not for the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours and Oriſons of holy men, and for thoſe Prayers and ſweet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes of their <hi>Aarons</hi> who are fain to ſtand betwixt the Porch and the Altar, and cry — <hi>Quis teneros oculus mihi facinat agnos</hi>— O ye fooliſh Galateaes, I would ſay Galathians <hi>who hath bewitched you.</hi> Now were this wantonneſſe in the weaker Sex alone, their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe might be born with, but when men ſhall be —<hi>Ut faemina com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pti,</hi> of the ſame complexion, and in the ſame condition — <hi>Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum admiſſi riſum tineatis amici.</hi> Could you refrain laughing? Yes, but not weeping, for ſhould <hi>Democratus</hi> himſelf come into ſome of our Churches, he would alſo change his countenance, and turn his ſmiling into mourning. Thus we may ſee their lameneſſe in coming to the Church, and careleſſe carriage in the Church. Which — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or laſie gout, the Phyſicians will tell you that it cometh from <hi>Bacchus</hi> or <hi>Venus,</hi> or from both, which being both hinderers of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they that are devoted unto them, cannot, as is ſaid, keep the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath without breaking of the Sabbath; When others, peradventure, not ſo great ſinners as they, although the Tower of <hi>Saloe</hi> hath fallen on ſome of them, would be glad that not for pettilaſonies, but petty lapſes they might have no harder penance impoſed on them than to go on foot, yea barefoot as farre unto their Pariſh Churches, though they were as far diſtant as from <hi>White-Hall</hi> to <hi>White-Chappel;</hi> For they for any offence concerning the Law of their God ſo that they may be freed from the fiery trial, ſhall be injoyned a Pilgrimage to travel as far as from <hi>Dover</hi> to Saint <hi>Davids,</hi> it being one of the directeſt Diami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of our Land, and above three hundred miles diſtant; Nay, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time they muſt petition their Confeſſors, that though they do dwell as far as the Orcades from St. <hi>Davids,</hi> that they may go in their Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage twice from thence to St. <hi>Davids,</hi> that they may thereby ſave their going once to <hi>Rome.</hi> For this is their Rule</p>
            <q>Roma ſemel quantum bis dat Menevea tantum.</q>
            <p>and that we may learn obedience of them, and yet not be partakers of their Sacrifices, or of their ſufferings; you in plainer termes may underſtand how their ſufferings are qualified—</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45328:5"/>
               <l>What Pilgrim to Saint <hi>Davids</hi> twice doth come,</l>
               <l>Doth ſave his penance going once to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>There are another ſort of Claudicants or haulters in devotion crept into the Countrey, who ſcorning to go upon Crutches, or our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayers, as they terme them; are divers times in ſuch pain in producing their — <hi>Periſſologies</hi> or home-ſpun kind of praying, that their faces are disfigured, as the Phariſees are with faſting, being alſo in the ſame condition as the philoſopher was, who having a <hi>Xanctippe</hi> to his wife, ſaid, — <hi>Non poſsum cum te vivere nee ſine te,</hi> I cannot well live with thee nor without thee. So theſe Battologiſts cannot be perſwaded to pray in that forme which they are taught, and yet know not well how to pray without it; who preſuming alſo on that ſaying of our Saviour — <hi>Dabitur in illa hora,</hi> it ſhall be given to you in that hour what you ſhall ſpeak, do not care for an hour together what they do ſpeak when they pray, as appeareth by their ſpeaking; But had they that love unto Chriſt or to his Church as they do pretend, they would be glad to creep unto him with thoſe Crutches, when well without them they could not go. Now as there is a Claudicancy or lameneſs <hi>in Officio,</hi> or in duty, both in ſlow coming to the Church, and ſlender ſerving of God in the Church. So our Sacrifices (which ſhould be without blemiſh, ſince they are to be offered in the Church) are divers times lame and defective, both in the matter and in the forme. Firſt, if our ſacrifice be of meal, it being the material of many Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Sacrifices, it muſt be of the fineſt of the meal, it muſt not be Farrago, or courſe flower, but — <hi>Cribro decuſſa farina</hi>— well ſifted, well ſearched, and the pureſt, for ſuch <hi>Abraham</hi> provided for the three Angels which came unto him. Next, there muſt be no meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeline, maſlin or mixture in it.—<hi>Mixo barbari</hi> — were Mungrils, and not thought fit to be Prieſts or Sacrificers, neither among the Grecians nor Barbarians, nor are ſuch—<hi>Hibrida ſacrificia,</hi> part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Enthuſiaſtical, partly phantaſmatical, without premeditation or preparation; proper Sacrifices or Oblations to be offered unleſſe on ſome — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Heathen Altar, but not on any — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Altar of God. Therefore if our Sacrifice be of meal (as is ſaid) <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> muſt make it ready for the Mill, and St. <hi>Paul</hi> muſt grind the grain when it is made ready, for ſo they agree.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Grana molenda gerit <hi>Moſes</hi> Legem tribuendo,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Paulus</hi> grana terit vim legis diſcutiendo.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The meal muſt be ground neither too high nor too low, too great nor too ſmall, for ſo advantge may be made, and men may take more
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45328:5"/>than is their due, and go beyond their allowance — <hi>Mediocria ſirma,</hi> — Moderation muſt buſwife it, and diſcretion muſt order it, and take away all the Bran out of it, — <hi>En chema en thora,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Rabbi,</hi> — If bran be in the meal, it will be as bad as corruption in the Law, or <hi>Colloquintida</hi> in the Pottage; and we may cry — <hi>Mors in olla,</hi> There is Death in the Pot, there is Sin in our Sacrifice. So then, whether our Sacrifices are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, preparation for the Sacrifice, or the Sacrifices themſelves, there muſt be no mixture, unleſs it be of Piety with Purity, and ſo they will be — <hi>Libamina,</hi> acceptable Sacrifices unto the Lord. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, If the Sacrifice be of fleſh, it muſt not be of all fleſh, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of mans fleſh, for <hi>Mummy</hi> is an abomination, as I ſhall tell you anon; nor of fiſh, and yet we read of no curſe they had to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it; nor of birds, unleſs of Turtels or young Pigeons; nor of beaſts, unleſs of ſuch as chaw the Cud, and that was the reaſon that ſeven pair of ſuch were preſerved in the Ark, when but one pair of all the reſt; nor of thoſe clean beaſts at all times, all the fleſh, but the beſt and fatteſt of the fleſh, that as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Le. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>it may be a ſweet ſavour unto the Lord;</hi> and this Rule was among the religious, — <hi>Sacrum pingue dabo: non macrum Sacrificabo,</hi> I will make no feaſt unto my God, but what ſhall be of the fatteſt and the faireſt that I have. And from this word — <hi>Maza,</hi> or fat, all feaſts former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had their names, as <hi>Lammaze-day, Candlemaze-day,</hi> and the like; not that they came from the word — <hi>Miſſa</hi> or <hi>Maſs,</hi> or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the — <hi>Catechumeni,</hi> ſuch as were not fit to be communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants; nor from the Hebrew word — <hi>Maſſah,</hi> a morning Sacrifice, which were more proper; but from — <hi>Maza</hi> — as is ſaid, for <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze-day</hi> was a feaſt of fat Lambs, dedicated to <hi>Luperca,</hi> that ſhe might preſerve their flocks from the Wolf, long before the Maſs was ever dream't of; and now becauſe thoſe <hi>Lupercalia, Carmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, Paganalia,</hi> and the reſt of them were <hi>Jubilees</hi> and feaſts of joy, and becauſe on ſuch dayes the fatteſt of their flocks they though the fitteſt for their feaſts, therefore <hi>Chriſtmaze-day</hi> and <hi>Michaelmaze-day</hi> deſerving ſuch feaſts, the one for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Nativity,</hi> the other for <hi>Michael</hi> his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictory,</hi> have their names from thoſe feaſts, as <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> ſtill retaineth its name from the <hi>Saxan</hi> goddeſs <hi>Eoſter,</hi> who had her feaſt before the Reſurrection. There is one thing more to be obſerved in the matter of theſe Sacrifices, they muſt be <hi>Holocausta,</hi> — <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictimae integrae aris impoſitae,</hi> perfect, without any imperfection, if but one limb be lacking, it will be a lame oblation; and if all the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45328:6"/>Sacrifices fatted on <hi>Hermon,</hi> ſhould fall or be ſlain on <hi>Zion,</hi> (or elſe how could the dew of <hi>Hermon,</hi> being a low hill, fall upon <hi>Zion</hi> which was an high hill?<note place="margin">Pſal. 133.</note>) I ſay, that if of an hundred Hecatombs but one hoof ſhall be wanting, they will all of them be but lame Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices; and therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> told <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that of all their Cattel they muſt not leave one hoof behind, for thereof muſt they Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice unto their God. Now as our Sacrifices may be lame in reſpect of the matter, ſo in the manner; and although Ceremonies (by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) are ſuppoſed to be ſuperſtitious, yet <hi>Selemo Jarchi</hi> ſaith that they are — <hi>Segil</hi> — or hedges invironing the Vineyard; and <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>If thou take away the hedge, the Serpent will bite thee.</hi> So then, Ceremonies not intrenching upon the Prerogative of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, may be requiſite in our Sacrifices, eſpecially ſuch as ſhall have any relation to obedience; and if <hi>Obedience</hi> be better than <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> as <hi>Samuel</hi> told <hi>Saul,</hi> then Sacrifice of neceſſity muſt be bettered by obedience; and this is ſhewed by bowing the body, and bending the knee, both being proper poſtures for expiating Sacrifices, and where this obedience is not performed, there is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or gout in the knee, or a dead Palſie totally diſperſed through an ill diſpoſed body. When <hi>Carmenta</hi> had not yet invented letters, from whom cometh <hi>Carmen,</hi> or a Verſe, and when ſhe knew not where to write them, but-<hi>in libris</hi>— the barks of trees, from whence cometh— <hi>Liber</hi>—a Book, the ingenuous <hi>Egyptians</hi> did find a way by Hierogliphicks or Pictures, to expreſs their minds in writing the one to the other, <hi>viz.</hi> a violent man by a Lion Rampant, a vinolent or ſwilling man by a Swine dormant, a laſcivious man by a Goat Saliant, a meek man by a Lamb Couchant, and the like. Among which we find two pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for our preſent occaſion. Firſt, <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Delborah</hi> kneeling at their Sacrifice on both knees, ſignifying Gods acceptance or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation. Secondly, <hi>Cain</hi> and his ſiſter <hi>Calmana</hi> kneeling at their Sacrifice, but on one knee, intimating rejection and reprobation. If God then was ſo diſpleaſed that there was a knee, and not a knee, or but one knee, when two were too little; how will he be offended when at our Sacrifices we cannot afford him one knee, but ſit as though we were ſacrificing the Sacrifice of fools, and what is fit for the back of fools,<note place="margin">Prov. 26.3.</note> you may ſoon find. When the wiſe men came with their oblations to Chriſt the King of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as they ſuppoſed only, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith <hi>Arius Montanus, Proſtrantes, Procidentes,</hi> as St. <hi>Jerom</hi> and <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> and the <hi>Genevaiſts</hi> themſelves ſay, <hi>fell down and worſhipped;</hi> The Original goeth farther, (if it be the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45328:6"/>Original, as <hi>Munster</hi> affirmeth it to be) uſing the Hebrew word <hi>Harets, They prostrated themſelves to the Earth, and worſhipped.</hi> What ſhall wiſe men think of thoſe that at their Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Oblations ſit or ſtand, and neither bow nor bend at all unto the King of the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> This King himſelf when he was to ſacrifice his ſoul for our ſins, though he could neither bow his body, nor bend his knee, being both bound too faſt to the Croſs, yet at the offering of it up he bowed as much as he could bow, for <hi>he bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his head, and gave up the ghoſt;</hi> and this may be ſufficient to teach wiſe men both what belongeth to humility and civility in all our Sacrifices whatſoever. There are yet another kind of <hi>Claudicants</hi> who are lame in their Benevolences, tributes, or rather retributions, in which they ſhould not be, if they were as they ſhould be. Firſt, Becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, That <hi>we have nothing but what we have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> and therefore on reaſonable conditions may more willingly part from it. Secondly, Becauſe <hi>Tully</hi> telleth us that — <hi>Non nobis ſolum nati ſumus,</hi> we are not born for our ſelves alone, and ſo goeth on, — <hi>Partem Patria,</hi> our Countrey will expect a part, which part is Conſtancy in our Countrey-men, who when they travel with the Prodigal into ſtrange Countreys, they ſhould read the learned work of a reverend Divine, called — <hi>Quo vadis,</hi> that they may know whither they do go, before they go, and be careful in the firſt place they do not change their Religion, unleſs it be ſuch a one as ſome of our new ones are, and then they need not fear, for no man will change with them. Next, they muſt be ſo far from <hi>Arminianiſm,</hi> that as judicious <hi>Zancheus</hi> ſaith, they muſt be neither <hi>Lutherans, Zuinglians, Calviniſt,</hi> but Chriſtians; and that they may ſo ſtill continue, they muſt not read <hi>Mariana</hi> the <hi>Scot,</hi> who will have Kings to be depoſed, if they be not of his peſtilent opinions; nor muſt they meddle with <hi>Molanus,</hi> who will have no faith with He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riticks, and yet they that are the chiefeſt Heriticks, muſt be judges of the Heriſies. And if a Prince ſhall diſlike that which they have a liking unto, nor Loyalty, nor Allegiance ſhall oblige them to do any thing but what they liſt, who will alſo ſo limit His Prerogative, that rather than He ſhall be <hi>in all Cauſes, as well Eccleſiaſtical as Civil, Supreme Head and Governour,</hi> they will take off his <hi>HEAD.</hi> And this is the <hi>Practice of Piety</hi> which of late hath been brought over into our Countrey, either by ſuch Tutors, or by their Diſciples, for want of Conſtancy at their return; Inſomuch that many men knowing what we have been formerly, and ſeeing what we are now,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45328:7"/>do admire to ſee our unconſtancy: <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great looking on ſome of our Engliſh features which were taken captive, ſaid — <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gli quaſi Angeli,</hi> The Engliſh are as Angels; but now our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Countreymen looking into our nature, ſay, <hi>Angle terre bonne terre mauvais gens, England</hi> is a good Nurſery, but the Nation is ill Nurtured. Nay, ſo unconſtant are we, or rather careleſs, that we have forgot our own Mother Tongue, for our ancient Language which was — <hi>Lingua monoſyllabica,</hi> a Language of one ſyllable, may now be termed — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or a confuſion of Languages, where by putting new pieces of cloth into an old veſture, thinking to make it better, make it worſe. For, Engliſh of it ſelf without mixture, is not inferiour to any Language that ſeemeth to be of a higher nature. Firſt, The <hi>Hebrew, Siriak, Calde, Arabek, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, Egyptick, Saracen,</hi> and all the Oriental Languages, which may be ſo termed, as well becauſe their letters look Eaſtward, as that they are Languages of the Eaſt, have all dependance one upon the other, and have been corrupted, as appeareth by that <hi>Hebrew</hi> which was before <hi>Eſdras,</hi> and that which was after him. Secondly, the Illirick, Greek, French, Spaniſh, Roman, Italian, and all the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental Tongues ſo termed as well becauſe their Letters look unto the Weſt as that they are Weſtern Languages. I ſay, when in all theſe Languages there are ſo many — <hi>Seſquipedalia verba,</hi> or words of ſo many ſillables, that ſome of them will make an Hexamiter or long verſe. Yet our true Engliſh conſiſting but of one ſillable for the moſt part (as the Hebrew Radixes do of three letters) is ſo ſignificant, that it may well be termed our Mother tongue, becauſe in one ſillable you may finde not only the names of an innumerable company of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures both by ſea and land, but their natures alſo, as hot, cold, moiſt, dry, and all parts belonging to them, and to our own bodies, as a heart to ſigh and groane for want of grace; a hand at hand to help a friend, and give his bread unto the poor, who pine and die for want of it; an eye to weep and ſend forth tears for time ill ſpent, when all the time we have to live may not be long enough to repent for the ill ſpending of it, as hath been ſaid</p>
            <q>
               <l>Fleres ſi ſcires totum tua tempora menſem</l>
               <l>Rides cum non ſit for ſitan una dies.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The men of <hi>Ninive</hi> hearing that forty dayes ſhould end their dayes, made a <hi>Quadrageſſima</hi> or Faſt of thoſe forty dayes; not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving one day of feaſting in it, unleſſe it were — <hi>Feſtum cineris,</hi> a feaſt of aſhes, conſidering how ſoon to aſhes they might be turned,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45328:7"/>But we with thoſe in the dayes of <hi>Noa,</hi> eat, drink, marry, and are merry, caſt away all ſorrow, and yet with <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> do not know whether the day of our Viſitation may not be before to morrow. Now as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> are careleſs in keeping their Language from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, ſo the true <hi>Brittans</hi> are as careful to keep theirs from being corrupted; and though the <hi>Dialect</hi> may differ, yet the <hi>Idiom</hi> is ſtill the ſame, and not as much as an <hi>iota</hi> alter'd ſince firſt it was ſpoken, as appeareth by an ancient Manuſcript, being one of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms written in <hi>Welch,</hi> and ſo long ſince, that we need not inquire for any other Original, it being as likely to be penned by <hi>David,</hi> and writ with his own hand, as any Pſalm made by <hi>Moſes, Aſſaph,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſome of the words I have ſet down, and how they do agree with the writings of theſe times, any ingenuous Native ſhall be the Judge. <hi>Trugarog, a glaſ-lawn yw'r Arglwydd hwyrfrydic i lid a mawr o drugarogrwydd. The Lord is full of compaſſion, ſlow to anger, and of great mercy.</hi> Thus we may ſee, that how careful ſoever others are, yet we are careleſs of all ſuch thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s as do concern us, and all for want of conſtancy. And ſo we come to Courage, which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing that is required, which muſt be performed as often as any lawful cauſe is offered; concerning which Courage, though every man cannot be a — <hi>Mucius Scevola</hi> — to fly into the fire to ſave his Countrey from the flame, yet he muſt not be a — <hi>Mecius Cepheſies,</hi> to ſit ſtill and be of no ſide, when there is occaſion of ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: And if a man be a <hi>Mephiboſeth,</hi> and not fit to fight, then he muſt with <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> come by night and ſhew his love unto his Lord with ſuch accommodation as may be conſonant to his condition. Firſt, when flags of defiance are ſet up at Sea, when fire and water do ſtrive which of them ſhall out-rore each other, we muſt not like cowards, creep into our Cabins, or get within the gable; but with Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> follow-paſſengers, every man muſt be doing ſomething, that all may not be undone. Secondly, when bullets are flying in the field, we muſt not with the Ephraemites, turn our backs, and run away ſo faſt, that we ſhall out-fly the bullets; but obſerve the word of Command given to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Stand,</hi> as a Statue, though the ſtorm be never ſo tempeſtuous. And now as our Countrey hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected her part, ſo <hi>Tully</hi> hath appointed the next part for our Parents, to whom we muſt not with the Hypocrites, cry, — <hi>Corban,</hi> prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a feigned Sacrifice before a filial Obedience; but with the Stork, — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, who when their Dams are aged, and not able to help themſelves, do nouriſh them as they were nouriſhed by them
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45328:8"/>when they were young. But if we will not learn of birds, we may learn of men, <hi>Anchiſes</hi> when he was left in the <hi>Trojan</hi> flames, his ſon <hi>Aeneas</hi> did not fear the fire, but ran into it, bearing his father on his back, and bringing him out of it, having more ſmell of the fire about him than the three children had when they came out of the fiery furnace: We read alſo of a daughter, who when her father was to be ſtarved in priſon, did feed him ſo long with her breaſt-milk un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to his enemies, that her piety at laſt being perceived, the daughter was praiſed, and the father pardoned. But many of us are ſo far from this piety, that we are like thoſe <hi>Hippopotami,</hi> or ſavage creatures who are the death of their Sire for the inſatiable deſire they have of their Dam; or like <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Spiders, or Saint <hi>John</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts Vipers, who enjoy their life by the death of their genitors; or elſe why hath it been ſaid as it is ſaid in St. <hi>Matthew</hi> — <hi>Filius ante diens parrios inquirit in annos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 21.</note> the children ſhall riſe up againſt their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and cauſe them to die. The laſt part that is expected of us is from our friends, where although every man cannot be a <hi>Damon</hi> and <hi>Pythius,</hi> a <hi>Pilades</hi> and <hi>Orestes,</hi> a <hi>Jonathan</hi> and a <hi>David.</hi> Yet he muſt be — <hi>alter idem</hi> — <hi>&amp; ad aras,</hi> both as one and one unto the end — <hi>Unas bodas,</hi> in Spaniſh ſignifieth a married couple, or a wedding. And though friends have not one body as man and wife have or ſhould have,<note place="margin">Joh. 2.1.</note> yet they ſhould have but one ſoul ſympathiſing both in their ſorrows, joys and ſufferings. There were in the memory of a man two — Didymi or twins, who as it ſhould ſeeme, had but one ſoul betwixt them, for the firſt-borne was lively, chearful, and fell to the ter, the other lay like a child ſtill-born, having ſo much heat only that there was hope of life; and in thoſe conditions they both continued about ſix hours, but when the ſoul had acted its part with the firſt-born, ſhe began to enter into the other, and then the firſt-born began to droop, and the later grew as lively as the former did before, and ſo continued in their viceſſitudes and ſtrange intercourſes ſix dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, keeping life and death betwixt them; at laſt the ſoul being weary and tired as it were, with ſo many tranſmigrations, departed from them, laving them both dead in that order as ſhe gave them life. Such a ſoul ſhould be betwixt two friends, the one willing to leave his joy, that the other might not grieve; the other to loſe his life, that the other might live — <hi>Nam ſic Eurioli Perithoique fides,</hi> ſuch formerly was the love of friends, and ſuch ſhould be their love unto the end. But the love of friends in theſe our dayes is not unto the end, but for ends. — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, who hath a friend, hath a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45328:8"/>treaſure, ſaith <hi>Periander;</hi> but he might as well have ſaid, he that hath a treaſure, hath a friend, for ſo ſaith <hi>Job, wealth maketh many fri nds, but poverty ſeperateth a mans neighbours from him. — Meander</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condeth both <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>Periander</hi> — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. — He that hath a table, hath a friend, but he that hath no ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, hath no friend, and ſo ſaith <hi>Ben Sirach,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclus. 6.10.</note>
               <hi>There is a friend at thy table, but he will not continue in the time of affliction.</hi> The birds would never have come unto <hi>Abrahams</hi> bare Altar, but when the Sacrifice was on, he could hardly beat them off: <hi>Where the bodies are,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>the Eagles will reſort.</hi> Which words, as they have admitted ſundry contrary conſtructions, ſome of them aluding to what hath been ſaid, ſo it may admit this one conſtruction more, that is, where bodies are ſubject unto ſin, eſpecially unto that ſilly ſin of ſelf-love, there the flatterers love to flock together. Who, as Carrain Crows, pick out the eyes of rotten ſheep while they are yet alive; ſo the flatterers pick out the eyes of thoſe that love to be flattered, inſomuch that they have not ſence to ſee how much they ſuffer in being ſo abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and as in the Epigram— <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>— the Crow and the Flatterer in Greek, as they differ but in a letter, <hi>Corax</hi> a Crow, <hi>Colax</hi> a Flatterer, ſo they differ not much in the matter, both by nature being devourers, the one when a man is dead, the other while he is alive. Firſt, ſuch flattering friends had <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> who being fortunate in all his fights, was perſwaded by his Sichophants that he was a God, and begot by the God <hi>Amos,</hi> and not of <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon;</hi> but being afterward wounded in a bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, cried out — <hi>Hiccine ſanguis</hi> — do the gods uſe to bleed ſuch blood as this? and upon his recovery did baniſh all flatterers out of his Court, as <hi>Urbanus Octavus</hi> did all Jeſuites out of <hi>Rome.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuch flatterers <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jehoſapha:</hi> had, perſwading them to go up to <hi>Ramoth Gilead,</hi> promiſing proſperity, but <hi>Ahab</hi> being wounded, found that all the balme in <hi>Gilead</hi> could not help him. Thirdly, ſuch a friend had <hi>Faustus,</hi> if any faith may be given to his Hiſtory, whoſe name was <hi>Mephauſtophilus,</hi> who made him do more miracles than all <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his Magicians could do, but withal did cheat him by a Bill of exchange, which was much after this manner — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>— giving him Braſs for Gold, or making him enjoy the pleaſures of this World for a ſeaſon, and then ſeized on his Soul: But had <hi>Fauſtus</hi> looked into the nature of the name of his flattering Familiar, he would have found that — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>— <hi>Mephauſtophilus</hi> had been no friend to <hi>Faustus,</hi> no more than ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45328:9"/>are, who are Favourites unto many: That friend then that muſt have ſuch a part as <hi>Tully</hi> ſpeaketh of, muſt be ſuch a one who by his Councel may cure all our claudicant and lame diſeaſes. Firſt, Of our <hi>Podagra,</hi> or Lameneſs in coming to ſerve God. Secondly, Of our <hi>Genogra,</hi> or Slovenly Behaviour in our Sacrifices, or ſerving God, conſidering alſo that the want of the wedding-garment in the Goſpel may be want of this our ſivility. Thirdly, to cure us of our Chiragra or lameneſſe in our hands where by we cannot ſuppeditate or help thoſe that ſupport us, to whom we ſhould be in our benevolences Rhetoricians with open hands, as Gods hands are open unto us, and nor Logicians, with ſuch clutcht fiſts and withered hands that— <hi>Citius fust um ex manu Herculis</hi>— men ſhould ſooner wreſt a clubbe out of the hand of <hi>Hereules,</hi> than any benevolences out of our hands that ſhould come either to God or his Vicegerents. We read of a malevolent company of hide-bound members, who preſcribing ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence to the appetite, and debarring the belly of its due, within a ſmall time— <hi>Paller in ore ſedit macies, in corpore toto</hi>—their froward faces grew formidable, and each member grew <hi>macilent</hi> and leane, inſomuch that they all looked like <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his leane kine, as all malicious men will do that pine away with repining at other mens proſperity. Of which Envie thus</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Envie, though the moſt hatefuleſt ſin of all the ſeven deadly ones, yet ſhe hath one good quality in her—<hi>Suppliciumque ſuum eſt</hi> — ſhe hurteth none but her ſelf; And in ſuch condition are all thoſe who are coſtive in their contributions and benevolences, eſpecially to thoſe that are their beſt Benefactors. For on ſtrict examination we ſhall find that a ſubject hath nothing that he can properly call his own, but what he hath from his Soveraign. Firſt, it is true, that our Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips do deſcend from our anceſtors, but who doth defend them? doth not the ancient Law? and who doth defend the Law? doth not the King? Yes, nor doth he only defend the Law, our Liberties, our life, but our Religion alſo, for He is the Defender of our Faith. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is true, that we have our lives from our natural fathers and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but what is nature without a Nurſe? Kings and Queens are our nurſing Fathers and nurſing Mothers:<note place="margin">Iſa. 49.23.</note> and <hi>Moſes</hi> his life was not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by his mother as ſhe was his mother, but as ſhe was the Nurſe whom <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s daughter had provided for him. There was a queſtion among the Moraliſts, <hi>Whether</hi> Alexander <hi>was more behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45328:9"/>to</hi> Ariſtotle, <hi>who was his Tutor to inſtruct him, or to</hi> Philip <hi>his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that did beget him?</hi> It was held Affirmative on the Tutors ſide. And thence it will follow, <hi>That we are more beholding to Him by whom our Eſtates are defended, than to them from whom they are deſcended.</hi> Such a <hi>Protector</hi> of our Eſtates, ſuch an — <hi>Omen,</hi> or <hi>Foster-Father,</hi> as the Hebrew termeth Him, have we, who is a Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſher and Cheriſher even of His Churliſh Children, and well may He be termed an — <hi>Omen,</hi> who was Deſtined and Ordained for our Deliverance, when we were left as <hi>Perdues</hi> in Deſpair; from whom alſo we have received ſo many favours, and by Him do daily enjoy, by Gods great mercy, ſo many bleſſings, that we may juſtly ſay, — <hi>O for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatos nimium bona ſi ſua norint — Angligines.</hi> — Our Lot is fallen in a fair ground; yea, our Fortunes, by the fruition of Him, are too fair, unleſs we had — ſome of us — more grace to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it. Had we an <hi>Abimelech,</hi> an Uſurping Bramble, who would Bathe and Imbrue his hands in the blood of his Brethren, or one, of whom it might be ſaid, — <hi>Omnia te adverſum ſpectantia nulla re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſum — Conspicimus.</hi> — We ſee all Goods come to thee, but no Good come from thee. Than to have ſaid, <hi>Nolumus hunc Regnare,</hi> This Man ſhall not Reign over us, had been a Noble Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution: Then to have inquired whether the <hi>P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLICK-FAITH</hi> had any Executor or Adminiſtrator, who ſhould ſecure thoſe Sums which a man ſhould lend, had been in earneſt (as one asked in jeſt) a diſcreet queſtion: Then with old <hi>Piſo,</hi> to have ſaid, — <hi>Parcatur ſumptui?</hi> — To what end is this waſte? had been worth the asking: Then with the ill Neighbour in the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> to have ſaid, — <hi>Non ſum, non poſſum, non libet, eſſe domi.</hi> — I cannot lend to day, come again to morrow, the Anſwer might have been tolerated; and if the morrow had been leſs apt to lend than the day, that day had been the better. But when there was a Man ſent from God, yea, and by an admired Miracle; when a <hi>Cato</hi> — <hi>Nuper de Coelo.</hi> — Newly, as it were, come down from Heaven: when we had a King that ſought not our Lives and Eſtates, but our Good; yea, and more than His own, What good man ſhould think any thing too good for Him? The <hi>Jewes,</hi> queſtioning with Chriſt whether they ſhould give Tribute to <hi>Caeſar</hi> or not, yet when they ſaw <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Image and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription, which was, — <hi>Augustus auguſto Deo: Auguſtus</hi> giveth himſelf to God; the very ſight of the Tribute-money made them ſilent, and ſilence gave conſent that they ſhould give Tribute unto <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and yet there was never ſuch a Tax as at that time:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45328:10"/>But we not only do daily ſee the Image of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> but <hi>Caeſar</hi> Himſelf, and in that <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the Image of God; yea, and more viſibly in Him, than in any other Man, by reaſon of his <hi>Vicegerency;</hi> who alſo is as much dedicated to God, as <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> could be; and yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of us, not only make a queſtion whether we ſhould give Tribute unto Him or not, but are ready with thoſe fooliſh <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> to give away out ear-rings, and other ſilverlings, to ſet up again ſome gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Calf. But if they had ever heard of — <hi>Ibice grues,</hi> or <hi>Solomons</hi> birds in <hi>Eccleſiastes,</hi> the one by revenging the murder of <hi>Ibis,</hi> the other by revealing the very thoughts of any Conſpiracies againſt a King, there would not be ſo many <hi>Achitophels,</hi> or brethren without grace and wiſdom, as their names do ſignifie, who with <hi>Ahab</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king counſel of more than four hundred falſe Prophets, make <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin, and if not in contriving, yet by conſenting, and if not in conſenting, yet in conniving, and not preventing all ſuch Plots as ſhould be pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udicial to His Perſon, or His Prerogative. <hi>Pilate</hi> did not only waſh his hands, as being innocent of Chriſts blood, although he was a ſtranger unto him, but uſed all the means he might poſſible to prevent it, he knowing, that they who were not with <hi>Jehu,</hi> were with <hi>Jezebel;</hi> and what judgments God ſent upon <hi>Jezebels</hi> juggling, in ſending forged Letters up and down to have her bloody deſigns take effect, the portion of <hi>Jezreel</hi> will inform you, where the very Dogs did ſcorn to touch thoſe hands of her, that had ſo great a hand in innocent <hi>Naboths</hi> blood. But for all this—<hi>Ambubaiarum Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legia: Cotton</hi> and his Colledge, <hi>Liola</hi> and his Diſloyaliſts, <hi>Parnel</hi> and his Partners in <hi>New Englands</hi> Conclave, do dayly cry—<hi>Nolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Carolum, volumus Olivarum,</hi> We will have no <hi>Barſabas,</hi> no <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jonas, Not Him, but Barrabas;</hi> and if this were not the language of the Legion, for <hi>they are many,</hi> why ſhould ſo many—<hi>Epicuri de grege porci,</hi> who for want of ringing, lie rooting and digging, as it were, at that diſmal dormitary of them that deſerved it, and cry with the Malevolent old man— <hi>Antigonum fodeo,</hi> I would have Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies Antagoniſt govern us again; which if it were not ſo, why ſhould ſo many men of fair fortunes, dayly foment new Factions to make themſelves unfortunate? They that are skilled in the <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manticks</hi> and <hi>Pyromanticks,</hi> can tell you that there are ſtrange ſpirits in them both, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iz. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſago</hi> in the one, and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iago</hi> in the other. Firſt, In <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſago</hi> there is—<hi>Vas</hi>— the veſſel of wrath, the head hatching miſchief by counſel at home. Secondly, In—<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iago</hi> there is—<hi>Vis,</hi> force of Arms, acting violence by the hand abroad; and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45328:10"/>in what particular places they have been acted, God grant they never may be acted again; and that we may—<hi>Parcere perſonis, &amp; dicere de vitus</hi>— not ſpeak of the offendors, but of their offences, this we may ſafely ſay, That they have been bountiful in their Benevolences, but —<hi>Cui bono,</hi> or to what good end we cannot ſay: for what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers gain by all their great Summes: not a freedom with the Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion, but a thraldom; not their liberty, but a ſlavery; and this was, becauſe they did not pay their Tributes unto <hi>CAESAR,</hi> but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe that were not <hi>CAESARS</hi> friends. And now what did they purchaſe by thoſe large loanes, but a long <hi>LENT,</hi> and not of ſix-weeks, but of more than ſix years? For as <hi>Lent</hi> was wont to be known by lean cheeks, pale faces, and poor clothes; ſo in their ſtreets ſome did appear like. Anatomies, or walking graves, others as walking to their graves, a third ſort as newly riſen from their graves, multitudes of men, women and children, walking half famiſhed in the fields, all repreſenting the <hi>Millinary's</hi> firſt reſurrection, only ſtill retaining a few rags. The conſideration of which calamities, ſhould make men underſtand the meaning of the Moraliſt in that of — <hi>Magis carendo, quam fruendo;</hi> that is, Good things are never known while they are enjoy'd, and good men beſt lookt on when their places are void. <hi>Ariſtides</hi> ſome ſay was baniſhed from <hi>Athens</hi> becauſe he was— <hi>Virtutis verae cuſtos regiduſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſatelles,</hi> ſo juſt, that men thought themſelves injured by his equity; but when Juſtice was baniſhed with him, then <hi>Ariſtides</hi> was a good man— <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith the <hi>Kiliadiſt,</hi> a Brewes never taſteth ſo well, as when a man hath nothing but dry bread; and <hi>Darius</hi> never knew the taſte of good drink, but when he drank ſtinking water out of a dirty ditch; nor did <hi>Iſrael</hi> ever know the comfort in having a King, but <hi>when there was no King in Iſrael;</hi> for when there was no King in <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> and every man did what he liſted, ſee what they did; Will was then reaſon, and yet there was no reaſon in their will, as appeared in that High Court of Juſtice, or rather horrid <hi>Inquiſition</hi> of Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in which when a King asking whether there was any Court in which Reaſon might not be heard, anſwer was made Him by one of the Three Knights of the Road, who lieth buried by the high-way, <hi>This is that Court in which Reaſon ſhall not be heard.</hi> Secondly, When there was no King in <hi>Iſrael, — Dat veniam corvis vexat ſenſura Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbas</hi> — Carrian Crows were preſerved, and innocent Doves de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. Thirdly, When no King—<hi>Vivitur ex rapto</hi> — Harpies were the only Hawks, and no leſs than Princes were the Partridges.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45328:11"/>Fourthly, When no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi>— <hi>Non hoſpes ab hospite tutus,</hi> the brother did betray the brother to death; the Land was full of <hi>Fratricides, Patricides,</hi> and <hi>Regicides</hi> — <hi>Aſtrea</hi> running— <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinnis</hi> reigning, Virtue vaniſhing, iniquity abounding, and the love of many thereby growing ſo cold, that it was impoſſible— <hi>Quin la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niant mundum tanta eſt diſcordia fratrum</hi>— but for the <hi>Elects</hi> ſake, that any fleſh ſhould be ſaved: But for the <hi>Elects</hi> ſake thoſe dangerous dayes were ſhortned; and as the dayes of the year do begin to lengthen at the Feaſt of St. <hi>Lucy,</hi> ſo when our Light, our <hi>Phoebus,</hi> our <hi>Apollo</hi> began to appear, our <hi>Halcion</hi> dayes began to lengthen; nor as the dayes lengthened, was the cold ſtrengthened, but — <hi>Diffugere nives</hi> — the hoary froſts of frozen Charity began to flie; — <hi>Rediunt jam gramina campis</hi>— the ſtore of Corn, Oyl and Wine again encreaſed, which made us all have <hi>chearful countenances, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our hearts were glad.</hi> For now our Sun hath paſſed through all the ſurly ſigns of the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> and beginning with his Declining, He hath eſcaped <hi>Libra,</hi> who being weighed in the—<hi>Prudential Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance,</hi> was found neither too light in His Religion nor Converſation. Secondly, The <hi>Scorpion,</hi> whoſe venemous Tail, if it had but toucht Him, He had died for it. Thirdly, The <hi>Sagitary,</hi> who <hi>bend their bow, and ſhoot their Arrows at Him that is true of heart, even bitter words.</hi> Fourthly, The <hi>Capricorn,</hi> who with his Horn puſhed againſt the <hi>Host of Heaven,</hi> but in his greateſt ſtrength his <hi>Horn</hi> was broken. Fifthly, The <hi>Aquarius</hi> who laid wait in all the Sink-ports to ſurprize Him. Sixthly, The <hi>Piſcis,</hi> the two Fiſhes, the one the <hi>Fleet,</hi> the other the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> who would have had his paſtime in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if he could have made his fleſh food for the Fowls of the Air, or Fiſhes of the Sea. But the <hi>Trident,</hi> or rather the <hi>Trientitie</hi> who ſtilleth the raging of the Sea, and the Madneſs of the People by Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence did prevent it. Next for His <hi>Climax,</hi> or beginning to ariſe; He hath eſcaped the <hi>Aries</hi> at <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> the <hi>Taurus</hi> at <hi>Worcester,</hi> the <hi>Gemine</hi> or <hi>Juncto</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the <hi>Cancer</hi> or Crooked Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles every where, who make Religion Retrograde, and Reward go backward: He is now in <hi>Leo,</hi> in His full ſtrength, where we pray that</p>
            <q>
               <l>Qui Leo de Juda eſt, qui Flos de Jeſſe, Leones</l>
               <l>Protegat &amp; ſtores, <hi>Carole</hi> Magne tuos.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And that nothing may be obſcure which ſhould concern His honour, or His happineſs, who is the cauſe of our Conſervation, and the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion whereby we are come to pray again with underſtanding, here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Prayer again —</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:45328:11"/>
               <l>Who <hi>Juda's</hi> Lyon is, and Flow'r of <hi>Jeſſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy Lyons and Thy Flow'rs <hi>CHARLES</hi> ever Bleſſe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And ſo we leave Him to His next Degree, to—<hi>VIRGO,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ratherina Tereſa.</note> where we alſo pray that the <hi>Beloved Son born of the Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> may proſper Him and Her in their Proceedings. And now we come to our poor <hi>Criple</hi> again, who was cured by Chriſt, when all other Phyſicians had forſaken him: which is my Second Part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When my father and mother forſook me,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, the Lord ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth me up,</hi> not that his father was taxed with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or unnatural af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, or that his mother ſhould bring the Prophets impoſſibility to paſſe, <hi>that a mother ſhould forget her children;</hi> for <hi>David</hi> was not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, when he ſaid he was forſaken. Firſt, forſaken he was, left alone to the wide world, as we ſay, yet he was not forſaken, becauſe his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents forſook the world before they forſook him. So that when he was left alone, he was — <hi>Nunquam minus ſolus, quam cum ſolus</hi> — never leſſe alone, than when he was alone. And where it is ſaid—<hi>Deus ſolus</hi> — <hi>The Lord alone ſuſtained me</hi> — <hi>Solus</hi>—or alone hath relation as well to <hi>Davids</hi> ſolitarineſſe, as to Gods ſufficiency; for <hi>Davids</hi> father was not by him when he took the Lion by the beard, nor was his mother nigh him when he ſlew the Bear, and yet he was no more alone than he was when he went to fight againſt <hi>Goliah;</hi> for although <hi>Eliah</hi> and all his brethten left him, yet he had a ſufficient Second to aſſiſt him, for he told <hi>Saul, that the Lord who had delivered him out of the mouth both of the Lion and the Bear, would alſo deliver him out of the hand of the Philistine.</hi> Now as it was well for <hi>David</hi> that he was not alone when he was alone, having the Lord to help him; ſo it may be ill with thoſe that are alone, if their help cometh not from the name of the Lord, for they cannot be alone neither, though they are alone. Firſt, the Lunatick in the Goſpel was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, not becauſe there is one beſide himſelf, as ſome will have it, but becauſe there is one ready to caſt him into the fire, or into the water, and then moſt ready when he is alone. Secondly, a melancholy man is not alone becauſe he is— <hi>Aut Angelus, aut Diabolus</hi> — he hath a good Spirit or a bad Spirit alway attending on him. Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> had a good Spirit attending on him, when he was alone, or elſe his—<hi>Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquia</hi> had not been ſo full of ſanctity as they were. <hi>Saul</hi> had as bad a Spirit while he was <hi>Saul,</hi> as St. <hi>Austins</hi> was good, or elſe in his zeale he would not have made ſuch havock of the Church as he did. Nor had <hi>Saul</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Kiſh</hi> ſought to have killed <hi>David</hi> his beſt friend, if the Spirit of the Lord had not forſaken him, and a foul Spirit entred
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45328:12"/>in his roome; ſuch a Spirit had <hi>Abimilech</hi> above named, unto whom the Spirit of hatred was ſent, as it is in the—<hi>Septuagint,</hi> which Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> termeth—<hi>Non Spiritum malum, ſed Spiritum peſſimum,</hi> the Spirit of malice, which is the worſt of Spirits. But if a man cannot be alone, why doth the Spaniard ſay — <hi>Guardami Dios de mi,</hi> Keep me O God from my ſelf; The reaſon is, that if he ſhould be left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to his hot nature, and not have grace to qualifie it, he ſhould be left in a ſad condition. When a <hi>Rabbi</hi> ſaith—<hi>Marbe abadim, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be gazel</hi>— Who hath many ſervants, hath many thieves, it need not be meant of houſhold ſervants, ſuch as the cozening Steward, or the covetous <hi>Gehazi;</hi> the one robbing his Maſter of his Revenue, the other of his Reputation; but of home-bred ſences ſiding with—<hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumia,</hi> or our natural concupiſcence, who as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>— work ſtratagems againſt the ſoul. Secondly, When Chriſt ſaith, <hi>A mans enemies are they of his own houſhold;</hi> as the words may be ſpoken of a reviling <hi>Ziphora,</hi> or a rebellious <hi>Abſolon,</hi> or the like; ſo may they be taken myſtically of the Wife, which is the Will, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting Reaſon, which ſhould be the Husband; or of our corrupt affections, or fleſhly luſts, which are at ſuch enmity againſt the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that <hi>we cannot pleaſe God;</hi> which God foreſeeing, thought it not good for man to be alone; upon which words <hi>Rabbi Nathanael</hi> ſaid, —<hi>O habrutha, O mithutha,</hi> O let me die, rather than be left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to be nurtured by my own nature. And if we ſhould look back unto our—<hi>Unde domo</hi>—to the Rock from whence we are hewen, or the hole from whence we are digged, we ſhould not much glory in our Genealogy; for ſhould we derive our Pedegree from the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent—<hi>Umbri</hi> which were before the Flood, and did not periſh with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinners (as <hi>Pliny</hi> would perſwade us) yet unleſs we could find a former Creation, and an <hi>Adam</hi> —<hi>ex mediori luto</hi>— framed of ſome better mould than hitherto hath been formed, it would be never the better for us, ſince ſtill that would be ſpoken of us, which <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſhould ſeem to ſay —</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>That we are a froward and untoward Generation, hearing, and not hearing, becauſe not regarding what we do hear, nor conſidering— <hi>Quo tendimus omnes</hi>— to what end our deſtiny may drive us, do divers times come to an untimely end. Travellers who may talk any thing by authority, will tell us, That in a Library in <hi>China</hi> there are extant ſome Records of more than Thirty Thouſand years antiquity, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45328:12"/>that in them we may chance to find a — <hi>Proprotoplaſtus,</hi> an <hi>Adam</hi> before <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>Adam,</hi> and yet that ſhall be ſmall help to our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealogy, unleſs we can find an elder <hi>Eve</hi> from whom that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould be born, if he were not created. But to ſpare this inquiſition, we may examine what thoſe years are, which are multiplied to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands, and then upon the account we ſhall find that every month is an year; and ſo there being in every thouſand years twelve thouſand months, though their Records ſhould be of forty thouſand years antiquity, yet that <hi>Adam</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> mentioned, will be as ancient as any other <hi>Adam</hi> that may be imagined; St. <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith, that there was an <hi>Adam</hi> who was the Son of God; St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, there is an <hi>Adam</hi> which is the Son of <hi>Adam,</hi> and the Son of God; and if there ſhould be an <hi>Adam</hi> before theſe, then it might be ſaid, — <hi>Sic à Jove tertius Adam,</hi> that there is one nearer unto God, than either of the two which in Scripture are named, and ſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo might be miſtaken in his account, who ſaith, <hi>The firſt man Adam was made a living Soul, and the laſt man Adam was made a quickening Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> And again, <hi>The firſt man Adam is of the earth earthly, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond man is the Lord from heaven heavenly.</hi> So then as — <hi>Sapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum octavus quis fuit nondum conſtat</hi> — the eighth wiſe man of <hi>Greece</hi> is not yet found: ſo that man <hi>only</hi> muſt be the man that muſt find out that <hi>Adam</hi> who ſhall be before the firſt. And all that are deſcended from him the mean while may ſay with the Satyriſt — <hi>Stemmata quid faciant,</hi> or rather with <hi>David, What profit is there in my blood deſcended from my anceſtors, when I,</hi> with thoſe — <hi>Puteolani</hi> which are near — <hi>Avernus, go down into the Pit?</hi> And now taking <hi>Adam</hi> in his — <hi>Puris Naturalibus,</hi> he is but earth, and this earth of all the four Elements, is the coldeſt, and thence is it that man is cold in his devotion to God, cold in his charity to man, and cold in all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that ſhould come from him. Secondly, Take him from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damant or Diamo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, as ſome will have him: there he is the hardeſt, as in the other he is the coldeſt. So that we are of <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tus</hi> his breed, or deſcended from <hi>Deucalion,</hi> or from ſuch ſtones whereof children ſhould be raiſed unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> or from any ſtone that might be harder than any of theſe, if there might be any: for — <hi>Gutta cavat lapidem</hi> — the leaſt drop leaveth ſome impreſſion upon the hardeſt ſtone, but many drops — <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e cadendo</hi>— falling often from the eyes of Orphans, can leave no impreſſion on our ſtony hearts, for if they could, we ſhould caſt our bread upon the waters of <hi>Mara,</hi> even bitter tears of thoſe which at this day do weep for want of it. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45328:13"/>Derive <hi>Adam</hi> from <hi>Adma,</hi> the true Anagram of <hi>Adam,</hi> which was a City of <hi>Pentapolis,</hi> as red a ſoyl as that from whence <hi>Adam</hi> was deſcended; for it was a City built on blood; and yet as dry, as the Adamant was hard; for if there had been but one penitential tear in it, even that tear might have quenched the fire, and ſaved the City, and all the Citizens that were i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Adma.</hi> So then by the one we are — <hi>Genus frigidum,</hi> a frozen generation; by the other — <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus durum,</hi> an obdurate generation; yea, and ſo hard, that as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>And you as lively ſtones, are made a spiritual building;</hi> yet let us talk what we will of edifying, if we have not ſomething to hold theſe ſtones together, — <hi>Duro conduro non fanno muro</hi> — ſaith the <hi>Italian,</hi> Hard to hard will never make a Wall. Fourthly, By <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> we are—<hi>Genus ſicoculum</hi>— a dry-ey'd generation: Nor is this drouth confined to our eyes, but it is Hydropically diſperſed over all the parts of our body; yea, inſomuch that <hi>Eriſictho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> whoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or hot digeſture did devoure more than <hi>Bell</hi> or the <hi>Dragon,</hi> or whom St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſheet would not ſerve for a ſecond courſe, was not ſo hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry as we are thirſty: Our drouth exceedeth the drouth of Summer, or of the drouth of <hi>Synoſura,</hi> whoſe Bears about the Northern Pole would drink up the Sea, as ſome ſuppoſe, if they could come at it. Nay, our drouth or thirſt is greater than the thirſt of <hi>Tantalus,</hi> who — <hi>Quaerit aquas in aquis</hi> — ſuffereth drouth in a deluge, for we are dry while we drink, like unto the Horſe-leach—<hi>Nec miſſura cutem niſi plena cruoris hirudo,</hi> we being not ſatisfied, until we be ſuffocated; And what do we thirſt after? not after the Wine, but after the Vine; nor after the Vine, but after the Vineyard: that was it that <hi>Ahab</hi> ſought after, although it were the price of blood. But theſe — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or thirſters after blood, may know, that as drinking in the cold fit of a Fever increaſeth the fervor or heat of the Fever. So thoſe whoſe charity being cold, do long after this cup of cruelty, will increaſe the heat alſo of a greater fire. And now all that hath been ſaid, is to ſhew in what miſerable condition man is, where he is left to his own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, grace having forſaken him. Therefore ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>— <hi>Ve ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li</hi>— <hi>Wo unto him that is alone,</hi> not for want of warmth only, as in the text, but by reaſon of the warfare that is betwixt the willer and the worker, where the Spirit is willing, but the fleſh, though weak, will not ſuffer the Spirit to do what he would. The <hi>wo to him</hi> then <hi>that is alone,</hi> is not for want of heat only, as in the text, for a man were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be alone than to have ſuch a companion whereby he may—<hi>Caleſcere plus ſatis</hi>-have wo with his warmth. Firſt, had not <hi>Sechem</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:45328:13"/>felt the warmth of <hi>Dina, Dina</hi> might have been ſtill a chaſt <hi>Diana,</hi> and not an — <hi>indomita invenea</hi>—to go a gadding after may-games— <hi>quae non inventa reperta eſt,</hi> whom when <hi>Jacob</hi> found, found that ſhe was loſt. Secondly, had not <hi>Zimri</hi> found the warmth of <hi>Cosbi,</hi> but had been alone, all had been well; but Muſitians can tell you, that — <hi>Solus cum ſola</hi>—is a ſweet melodious tune, but the muſick is ſad, mournful and melancholy withal, and ſo it was with <hi>Zimri,</hi> and <hi>Cosbi,</hi> or elſe the bed of <hi>Cosbi</hi> had not been the bloody bath of <hi>Zimri,</hi> nor <hi>Zimries</hi> goar had been the grave of <hi>Cosbi.</hi> So then, a man may be <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> but not — <hi>Solitarius;</hi> alone, but not ſo ſolitary alone, but he ſhall have aſſociates: When Chriſt was in the wilderneſſe faſting alone, he was not long ſolitary alone; for — <hi>Silenus quamvis nemo vocaret adeſt,</hi> — Satan came tempting him to eat before his time: Again, when Chriſt was praying in the Mount of <hi>Olives</hi> alone, he was not long alone, though in a long Agony; for — <hi>Angelus en Chriſti ſolatus pectora</hi>— An Angel came from heaven comforting him in his agony. So then a man is not alone, when he ſeemeth to be alone; nor comfortleſs, when he ſeemeth to be comfortleſs; nor forſaken, when ſome think he is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken; for then ſome would be but in a ſad condition. Firſt, the poor are ſuppoſed by ſome to be forſaken when they beg their bread, becauſe <hi>David</hi> ſaith, — <hi>Nunquam vidi</hi> — <hi>I never ſaw the righteous forſaken, nor their ſeed begging bread;</hi> which in a charitable conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſheweth that they are not forſaken, though they beg their bread; for though the word — <hi>Derelictum</hi>-or forſaken, is not iterated or twice repeated, to avoid a tautologie, or words more than are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary; yet this is the honeſt meaning of them, <hi>I never ſaw the righteous forſaken, nor their ſeed forſaken</hi>— <hi>in begging bread.</hi> And if this were not <hi>Davids</hi> meaning, Why ſhould he ſay ſo ſoone after it, <hi>Bleſſed is the man that conſidereth the poor and needy, for the Lord will deliver him in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime of trouble;</hi> yea, <hi>and God himſelf will make his bed in all his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> Secondly, Why ſhould <hi>Solomon</hi> ſecond <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 41.1, 2, 3.</note> ſaying— <hi>Qui dat egeno, mutio dat Domino; he that giveth to the poor, lendeth unto the Lord, and he will ſee it paid again?</hi> Nor can I ſee any reaſon why our ſeeming religious men ſhould be ſo hard-hearted to the poor, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they be angry, becauſe Chriſt ſaid, That <hi>Lazarus</hi> the beggar was in heaven, and <hi>Dives</hi> the miſer was in hell. So then thoſe that are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed, muſt not be by <hi>David</hi> thought to be forſaken, for then <hi>David</hi> himſelf would be in the ſame condition. When the <hi>Idumii</hi> began to rebel againſt <hi>David,</hi> and when the ſons of <hi>Zervia</hi> were too hard for him; when the feminine faction, who like <hi>Sampſons</hi> Foxes, carried
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45328:14"/>fire in their tailes to kindle the coles of contention, and foment the flames of faction and rebellion againſt him, then— <hi>Congregatio tauro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum in vaccis populorum,</hi> not the beſt of the people, but the beaſts of the people, the —<hi>Opifices faeces,</hi> the ſpear-men, the fat Buls of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan,</hi> the leane kine of the Common, and all the horned heard compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him about, crying, <hi>God hath forſaken him, perſecute him, and take him, for there is no man to help him.</hi> But neither was the good King for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, nor his ſeed forſaken, for— <hi>Patrum virtus,</hi> the vertue of his Father was viſible in his Son, who reſtored all things that were ruined, both in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and in <hi>Sion,</hi> and grew in favor daily both with God and godly men. Laſt of all, our poor Creple might ſeeme to be forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, being diſeaſed thirty and eight years, but he was not forſaken, for — <hi>Medicus &amp; medecina</hi>— Chriſt being his phyſick and his Phyſician, did cure him when all other Phyſicians had forſaken him, ſaying, <hi>Take up thy bed and walk.</hi> And now ſince he is healed, we may have leaſure to enquire how he had been healed, if there had been any man to help him, ſince there are ſo many opinions concerning the nature of this <hi>Bethezda</hi> or <hi>Lazures</hi> bath. Firſt, ſome will have it natural only, as our waters are, either internal by potion, or external by lotion, which if it were ſo, there need be no Angel, (unleſſe as a Fee) to be a viſible Agent to ſtir the waters, for many are daily healed by the outward water, though few by the inward without any ſuch Agent. Secondly, Others will have this Bath of <hi>Betheſda</hi> to be accidentally ſanative, by reaſon of ſo many hundred Sacrifices as were uſually waſhed againſt their Feaſts in that water, where by the abundance of blood and other ſlimy ſubſtances reſiding as a ſediment in the bottom of the Pool, the bathing in it might be as beneficial to a lame man, as the warm belly of a beaſt which is uſual for any man to bath in that is lame; and then as there needed no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any Angel in the natural bath, ſo there muſt be no Angel in this accidental bath; For if the Angel were a Meſſenger ſent by man as an officer to ſtir the waters, or to raiſe up the ſlimy ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that the water might be the ſtronger; then the ſervant was more to be blamed for doing ſuch ſervile work upon the Sabbath day than Chriſt was, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h whom they quarreled, becauſe be healed only on the Sabbath day: By which we may ſee, that curious inquiſitors attributing more to nature than to grace, ſeeking to ſhun <hi>Silla,</hi> fall into <hi>Caribdis,</hi> and do as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>fearing Idolatry, commit Sacriledge,</hi> who by pulling down the pictures of Chriſt and his Apoſtles out of the Church-windows, break them all in ſuch ſort, that they make the Sanctuaries of God fit for nothing but to be habitations for <hi>Zim</hi> and <hi>Ohim,</hi> Oſtriges
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45328:14"/>and <hi>Satires,</hi> or ſuch unclean creatures as themſelves, and yet they that ſet up thoſe pictures, did not intend to ſet up Idolatry, or at leaſt Popery, becauſe ſuch pictures were up in many Churches before the name of Pope was ever known. But ſuch curious impertinents may underſtand that a man may be neither — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Images; nor <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a lover of Images; and yet he need not to be — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a breaker of Images. <hi>Damaſcen</hi> was a devout man, and loved Images<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and his retired Cell was hung round with them; yet he was ſo far from Idolizing or worſhipping of them, that he gave this Caution to the contrary.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Eſſigiem Christi cum ſpectes, pronus adora,</l>
               <l>Sed non Effigiem, ſed quod deſignat honora.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Not the Picture preſent, but the Party repreſented (if any thing) is to be worſhipped: there being a difference betwixt — <hi>Signum &amp; Signatum</hi> — as much as is betwixt the Shadow and the Subſtance. Suppoſe that <hi>Lots</hi> houſe had been an Inne, and the Angel had been the Sign, the Angel without could not have ſecured <hi>Lot</hi> from the rage of the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> it was the Angel within that pulled him into his houſe, and ſaved him, or elſe he had been pulled all to pieces: ſo in like manner there muſt be a difference betwixt <hi>adornation,</hi> and <hi>ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> betwixt adorning, and adoring: A man may adorn his Houſe with Pictures, as <hi>Damaſcen</hi> did, and yet neither Idolize them, nor adore them, and if ſome naked Pictures be among them, which were better abſent than preſent, yet if any idle imaginations ſhould be in the beholders, it is — <hi>Ad intus, non ad extra</hi> — from within, and not without. Firſt, Had we no way to expreſs our minds but by Hierogliphicks (as is already ſaid) and that we were to ſhew what Truth were, there would be no way to expreſs it better, than by the Picture of a Naked Woman, ſhe being termed — <hi>Nuda Veritas</hi>— The Naked Truth, having on her no Vail nor Viſard; and if there ſhould be any wandering or wanton thoughts in the Spectators look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on ſuch a naked Picture, — <hi>Ita concipit intus,</hi> would be the cauſe of it; the immodeſt motions come from the mind; the fault is neither in the Picture, nor in him who hath the Picture. Secondly, The Motto or Inſcription on the Garter, honoured be <hi>King Edward the Third,</hi> and Giver of the name to the chief <hi>King of Arms;</hi> when it ſaith — <hi>Honi ſoit qui mal y penſe, Evil to him that evil think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> it wiſheth evil to none but ſuch as think evil: So that if there were not evil in the thinker, there would be no evil in the wiſher. The ſupercilious <hi>Gimnoſophiſts</hi> need not to ſhew their nakedneſs, but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45328:15"/>that they have a mind to be naked. The laſcivious <hi>Adamites</hi> may be clothed if they pleaſe, but that they love to have their foul, uncome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly parts to be diſcovered: A beauty may behold her face in a Glaſs, yet neither be proud of it, nor with <hi>Narciſſus</hi> fall in love with it; — <hi>Non ſpeculum, ſed spectrum,</hi> it is not the face without, but the phancy within, which doth malificiate and bewitch the imagination; for divers times Deformity ſuppoſeth her ſelf to be a beauty, all which is made good by a ſaying of our Saviour, <hi>Not that which is without, but that which is within, doth defile a man.</hi> And, if there were not venome in the Spider, he could not make poiſon of that whereof the Bee maketh honey: <hi>Alpharabius, Aristotle,</hi> and other Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers make it a queſtion, Whether the ſight cometh by ſending forth the <hi>Spirits,</hi> or receiving in the <hi>Species;</hi> but this they may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That thoſe eyes do ſend forth evil ſpirits, which make the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject evil, which of it ſelf is good. Firſt, At the Bath —<hi>Hic ſedit ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noto juncta puella viro</hi>— here ſitteth an <hi>Adonis,</hi> there a <hi>Delilah;</hi> here a naked man, and there a naked woman, which to a modeſt mind moveth no more; than when a man looketh on a Mermaid, or a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid on a man, and if any thought ſhould ariſe, it ſhould be, That either of them is— <hi>Introrſum turpis specioſus pelle decora</hi>—ſo fair with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and ſo foul within, that they need more waſhing within, than without. Secondly, The beholding of thoſe naked Nymphs, to a religious man, is a repreſentation of the Reſurrection, and not only to conſider that as we came <hi>naked into the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3.18.</note>
               <hi>ſo naked we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn;</hi> but to take care that the ſhame of our <hi>nakedneſſe do not appear</hi> ſo much, that we may be glad of fig-leaves to cover it, if we could finde them; but if fig-leaves cannot be found, our offences will: for then there ſhall be no — <hi>Latitats</hi> or <hi>Writs</hi> of — <hi>Non inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>—all muſt appear, and every man muſt anſwer at the <hi>Tribunal Seat of Chriſt, and receive a reward for whatever hath been done in thoſe naked bodies, whether good or evil.</hi> When therefore in that Bath we ſhall ſee the water, we may not think on wantonneſſe, but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that <hi>the Sea must give up her dead,</hi> and ſo to have her diſcharge. When we ſhall ſmell the Brimſtone, that <hi>Hell muſt give up her dead,</hi> and not as the Sea, to have a diſcharge, but only to ſhew them, and ſhut them up again. Theſe ſhould be the uſes which men ſhould make of Images, and not to imagine that there muſt be Popery in them, or in Pictures, for there can be no Superſtition or Idolatry in them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we make it; For the Image is as you imagine it. According to which imagination, have been the various opinions about this <hi>Betheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:45328:15"/>which can be neither natural or accidental, as is already ſaid, but ſupernatural, where, an Angel from heaven, and not an Officer ſent by men, did make the water miraculous, as other waters in like manner have been made. Firſt, the water turned into wine at the marriage in <hi>Cana,</hi> neither the drawer, nor the bearer of it was the cauſe of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, but Chriſt or his Angel was the cauſe of it. Secondly, the water of <hi>Jordan</hi> of it ſelf could not cure the Leproſie of <hi>Naaman,</hi> for then the waters of <hi>Damaſcus</hi> might have done it as well. Thirdly, <hi>Silo</hi> having its name from being ſent, could not have cured blind <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timeas,</hi> if ſome Angel had not been ſent to ſanctifie it. Fourthly, the waters of <hi>Egypt</hi> turned into blood, were neither turned by <hi>Moſes</hi> his word, or by his rod, but by that Angel which made his rod to bud, which was as great a miracle, as turning the waters into blood. Fifth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the wine in the Sacrament turned into purer blood, though aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the word of the Miniſter, yet he is but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the voice, not the vertue of the Conſecration, though after the Conſecration it is converted; for the Miniſter is ſo far from knowing how to turn it,<note place="margin">John 6.55</note> that he knows not to what it is turn'd, no more than he knows how the bread is turned into Chriſts body A real preſence he may allow, becauſe Chriſt ſaid, <hi>My fleſh is meat indeed;</hi> but a corporal preſence he may not allow, becauſe he was corporally preſent when he gave the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Had thoſe words been ſpoken after his Reſurrection, there might have been a queſtion with what body he might riſe? whether with an — <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biquitary</hi> body or not; and yet it is improbable, that it ſhould be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biquitary,</hi> or in more places at once than in one. Firſt, Chriſt himſelf affirmeth that his body was a phyſical or natural body, which might be ſeen, felt, and underſtood,<note place="margin">Luk. 24.39.</note> he ſhew'd it to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that ſaw his hands, felt his feet, and by both underſtood, that it was that body which was wounded on the Croſſe. Secondly, that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was fixed unto the Croſſe, not a fugitive or fictitious body, as the <hi>Manichees</hi> and other mazed men imagine; and what is ſo confined to any one place, cannot be <hi>Ubiquitary.</hi> Could <hi>Mercury</hi> be fixed (as your Chimicks terme it) and ſtill remain <hi>Mercury;</hi> or could gold be made fluid or ſubtile, and again be made ſolid, then that Stone which ſhould make gold, would be feaſable, which only is phantaſtical; and by that ſtone, gold might be multiplied, which hitherto hath been on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diminiſhed. But as neither of theſe have ever been brought to paſſe, ſo Chriſts body being ſtill the ſame, and in the ſtate of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, cannot admit any alteration, for then it might be ſubject to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and ſo the Spirit of God would be contradicted, which ſaith,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45328:16"/>
               <hi>Thou wilt not ſuffer thine Holy One to ſee corruption.</hi> Thirdly, Chriſts body is framed of fleſh and bone, and not a ſpiritual body, as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf told his Diſciples, and was the ſame after his Reſurrection, as it was in his Paſſion, and ſhould ſo much of his fleſh be taken from his bones, as is dayly uſed in the Sacrament; I ſpeak it with reverence, there would be nothing but a Skeliton to ſit at the right-hand of God. But that may not be: For he aſcended with that body in which he roſe, having thoſe wounds on it as were when he was crucified, and ſhall come again to judge the world with the ſame body wherewith he both ſuffered and aſcended,<note place="margin">Acts 1.11.</note> for ſo the Angels told thoſe that did ſee him when he did aſcend, ſaying, <hi>Ye men of</hi> Galilee, <hi>why ſtand ye ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing up unto heaven? This man ſhall come down again from heaven in the ſame mannner as ye ſee him go into heaven.</hi> Now as we may allow a <hi>real,</hi> but not a <hi>corporeal preſence</hi> in Chriſts body; ſo in the Wine turned into Blood; we muſt believe, that though the Wine be not turned into Blood, yet we may believe that his Blood is in the Wine, becauſe Chriſt alſo ſaid, <hi>My blood is drink indeed;</hi> and yet we do not read of any Blood that he had loſt before the words were ſpoken; wherefore omitting the multiplicity of opinions, as alſo the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Praepoſitions of <hi>Trans, Sub, Con,</hi> and <hi>Super,</hi> we may believe that in the Elements before they are made Sacraments, there are ſome <hi>Tranſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ients</hi> tranſcending the reach of humane reaſon, but — <hi>Quo mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>— or in what manner theſe tranſmiſſions are, or in what meaſure or manner Chriſts Body is in the Bread, or his Blood in the Wine, I think it modeſty not to meddle, but to refer it to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that at his coming he may reſolve the queſtion: Yet mean while, this we may ſay of this Sacred Sacrament.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>He was the Word that spake it;</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>He took the Bread and brake it;</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>His Body he did make it;</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>So I believe and take it.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And he that ſo taketh it, unleſs judicious men are miſtaken, take this not amiſs. Now as there are diverſities of gifts by the ſame Spirit, as ſaith St. <hi>Paul;</hi> ſo there are diverſities of operations wrought by ſuch Miniſters as God hath ordained by the ſame Spirit to work his Miracles, for the waters (as before hath been ſaid) have not only been turned into blood, but into fire, and that fire again into water; for — <hi>Baptiſmus fluminis,</hi> the Baptiſm of water, and — <hi>Baptiſmus flamminis,</hi> the Baptiſm of fire, are both one Baptiſm. Firſt, <hi>John</hi> baptizeth with water unto Contrition. Secondly, Chriſt baptizeth with fire unto Remiſſion, as may beſt be expreſſed by St. <hi>John Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptists</hi> own words, <hi>I indeed baptize you with water unto Repentance,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45328:16"/>but he that cometh after me, will baptize you with the Holy Ghoſt, and with ſire;</hi> The one ſaying, Repent and you ſhall be baptized; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Be baptized and you ſhall be ſaved. Which <hi>Aequitollence</hi> of contrary Elements, maketh a reconciliation of greater contrarieties. For Nature and Grace being in a <hi>Diametrical oppoſition,</hi> the Spirit and the fleſh at open defiance one againſt the other, yet now Grace, by this Baptiſm, beginneth to ſupply the defects of Nature, and the Spirit is willing to ſupport the weakneſs of the fleſh — <hi>Alterous ſic, — Altera poſcit opem res &amp; conjurat amicè</hi>—the Lyon and the Lamb have lien together; the Cocatrice and the Child have kiſſed each other. And yet for all this, that Sacred Sacrament of Baptiſm, which hath reconciled ſo many Millions of ſouls unto God who have been ſeparated from him by Original ſin, is now, among many, like an old Almanack quite out of date, and ſet behind the door, both in reſpect of the matter, and of the form. Firſt, Baptiſm it ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Free-hold of the Elect, and ſuch a Patrimony of Grace, that a child may claim his admiſſion unto it ſo ſoon as he is eight dayes old, muſt now be— <hi>Ad libitum Domini</hi>—deferred until the child be come to the years of diſcretion; who, if he doth — <hi>Paetriſare</hi>—or be like the Parents, will be — <hi>Ad Graecas Calendas,</hi> or never, ſince there was never any ſuch day in the Kalender. Secondly, For the form: The Font ſo termed, from being the fountain of grace, is like an old Fabrick, or houſe of Hoſpitality, quite out of faſhion, and in ſuch diſgrace, that a Barbers Baſon is preferred before it; which is only fit for a Midwife in a Chamber in a caſe of neceſſity, but far un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for a Miniſter in the Church, unleſs he want a Font or Conformity. In all which—<hi>Dum ſtulti vitant vitia in contraria currunt,</hi> we ſtrain at Gnats, and ſwallow Camels; ſtumble at ſtraws, and leap over blocks; who fearing Superſtition, fall into Judaiſm, as well in the Adminiſtration of Baptiſm, as of the Lords Supper. Firſt, Why ſhould not the Font, having been ſo many hundred years uſed in the Church to baptize children, be as convenient for the ſame uſe ſtill (as of late) in a Baſon, unleſs it were becauſe as the blood was in the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at the Paſsover, which was ſprinkled upon the door-poſts, ſo the water muſt be in a Baſon which is to be ſprinkled on the children which are to be baptized. But did we look into the Greek word— <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>— or the Latine word— <hi>Immergo</hi>— both being to duck under wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or to dip, ſignifying, That ſin is drowned, and the ſinner ſaved. We would imagin that the dimenſions of a baſon would be too ſhallow for ſo deep a myſtery. But as—<hi>Dato uno abſurdo ſequuntur mille,</hi> one
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45328:17"/>abſurdity granted, you may grant a thouſand; So from one Judaiſme we fall into ſo many, that decency and order once laid aſide, we ſhall think that all things are done decently that are done out of order, and ſo we ſhall ſtand when we ſhould kneel, ſit when we ſhould ſtand, and ſit at the Sacrament when we ſhould neither ſit nor ſtand, which is alſo done in a way of Judaiſm, ſuppoſing that the Diſciples did either ſit or ſtand when they did receive the Sacrament, or eat the Paſſeover. But— <hi>Lectis diſcumbentes</hi>—was not ſitting on their beds, which uſually ſerved them for tables, but leaning on their beds<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; this leaning might be done with more eaſe if they did kneel, but if they did not kneel, they could not well lean without bending the knee. But well may we diſlike the Ceremonies of the Church, when we do not like any thing that is ſubſtantial in the Church; for we are alway contending— <hi>De lana caprina</hi>—ſeeking knots in Bulruſhes, alway complaining, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have no cauſe to complain. Firſt, the Altar muſt not ſtand Alterwayes, nor the Common Prayer be ſaid at it, unleſſe we may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter both as we pleaſe. But the quarrel againſt the Book of Common Prayer, is not becauſe there is ſwearing and conjuring in the Letany; for we can ſwear, and forſwear it again, without any great ſcruple of conſcience, &amp; with <hi>Ligatures</hi> (if you read <hi>Agrippa</hi>) ſo bewitch one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, that we need no other conjuration. There is one other thing in the Common Prayers which doth trouble us more than any thing that is in the Letany: We may find that in the Introduction to the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination</hi> ordained to be uſed on <hi>Aſh-wedneſday,</hi> that <hi>Confeſſion</hi> and <hi>Penance</hi> is much to be deſired,<note place="margin">Pſal. 53 5.</note> which being deſired, we may fear that in time it may be required: but to any one ſo fearing, he may ſay, — <hi>Quid timeam ignoro tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o tamen omnia demens</hi>— which <hi>David</hi> doth Engliſh, <hi>They were in great fear, where no fear was.</hi> Now in this long digreſſion, leſt we ſhould forget our poor Creple who is not yet gone from the Bath of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> I muſt tell you, that there is one Bath more, in which the Angel muſt move the waters: It is a Bath of <hi>Brine,</hi> which is a ſingular good medicine for any Ache in the body, and as Soveraign for any Agony of the ſoul; it is not an ordinary brine, but diſtilled from the Alimbicks of the eyes; and as the Angel ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Rock, the waters ran in dry places; ſo alſo he ſtriking or clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our petrated hearts, the tears may make long furrows in our cheeks, but our cheeks are ſo much ſmoothed, that no ſuch furrows can be found in them; and tears are ſo precious, that God was fain to put <hi>Davids</hi> tears into bottles, foreſeeing that he ſhould find but few in future times. But I ſuppoſe that the Son of man found ſome tears
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45328:17"/>in our poor Creples eyes, or elſe he would have ſpoken to ſome of the reſt, as well as unto him, when he ſaid —<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>is ſanus fieri</hi>— Wilt thou have help? wilt thou be healed? Thou ſhalt have help, thou ſhalt be healed, perceiving alſo that he had lain a long time lame, and was not made whole, <hi>Becauſe he had no man to help him;</hi> which is my third part.</p>
            <p>When men are dying, ſaith <hi>Plutarch,</hi> the Lice will begin to leave them, unleſſe ſuch Lice as <hi>Herod</hi> and ſome other near home had ſent unto them as a judgment to devour them. When houſes are falling, ſaith <hi>Pliny,</hi> the Militia of Mice ſo termed in <hi>Batrocomiama hia,</hi> or the furious fight betwixt the Hilander and the <hi>Hollander</hi> will be upon their march to finde freſh quarters. The reaſon of the former is, they feeling the blood to grow cold, find ſmall comfort in their longer continuance: The reaſon of the other is, they feeling the wind got into the rotten holes of the walls, perceive as it were, an Earth-quake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the walls, and think it high time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to take their walk: Both which have an alluſion to that of <hi>Euripides,</hi> — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>— <hi>When the Birds are flown, no man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth the Feathers in the Nest: And when Fortune is on her wing, Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip will ſoon find wings to follow after.</hi> Firſt, If <hi>Craeſus</hi> become <hi>Codrus,</hi> and Poverty pinch the Prodigal, they both ſhall be eſteemed as they are, not as they were. Secondly, If <hi>Dives</hi> become <hi>Lazarus, Dives</hi> muſt leave his delicates, and be contented to dine with <hi>Lazarus</hi> among the Dogs. Laſt of all, When <hi>Homer</hi> with his <hi>Iliads</hi> and <hi>Odices</hi> did fit every man in his humour, then — <hi>Smyrna, Rhodos, Colophon, Salamis, Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os, Argos, Athenae,</hi> ſeven Cities were in contention who ſhould have him to be their Countrey-man, but if <hi>Homer</hi> grow poor, his Poems muſt be turned into Proverbs — <hi>Si nihilattuleris, ibis</hi> Homere <hi>foras — Homer</hi> muſt be no longer a <hi>Poet,</hi> but a <hi>Peripatetick,</hi> and walk about the Streets: which fortune hath befallen men of greater note, than have been named. Firſt, When <hi>Job waſhed his paths with butter, and his feet in oyle,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his fat paſtures, and multitude of milch Cattel depaſtured in them, then no ſooner did he appear, but the young unmannerly Courtiers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to fly to corners; but when he <hi>ſcraped his ſores</hi> with the <hi>Potſherds</hi> which the <hi>Sabeans</hi> had broken, then each boy did abuſe him; yea, and ſuch boyes, as he did ſcorn that their fathers ſhould have eaten with his Shepherds Dogs. Secondly, When <hi>David</hi> was young and active the <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels</hi> danced about him, and ſang, <hi>Saul ſlew his thouſand, but</hi> David <hi>his ten thouſand;</hi> but when <hi>David</hi> grew aged and diſeaſed, then the <hi>Druides, Bards</hi> and <hi>Bachides</hi> abuſed him in their Ballads, or uſing his own words, <hi>The very Drunkards made Songs of him.</hi> Such abuſive <hi>Bachides</hi> do every where abound, whoſe brains being intoxicated more with wind, than with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45328:18"/>Wine, do think that the Church, the State, and every mans eſtate ſtands tottering, and that all things are turning upſide down, when the —<hi>Vertigo</hi> is in —<hi>Vertice,</hi> and <hi>circulatio eſt in cerebro,</hi> the tottering and turning is not in the houſe, but in the head; and although the circulation of the blood hath been found out of late as a prety fancy, yet the circulation of the brain hath been long time found out, and not a fancy: which <hi>Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> cannot —<hi>quadrare,</hi> or agree with regularity; for then there would be—<hi>Quadratura circuli</hi>—which never was yet found out either in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, or in Divinity; for if the world being a circumference, cannot ſatisfie or fill the heart (as Divines ſay) being a triangle, how ſhall a <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference</hi> fill a <hi>quadrangle,</hi> which hath more corners than a triangle? So then as the Philoſophers cannot make that round which is ſquare; ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can the Divines make that ſquare which is round: Of which diſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant diſpoſitions are thoſe <hi>Aethiopian Cynocephali</hi> of <hi>Lycaons</hi> linage, which are ſent from <hi>Anticera</hi> into the Land of <hi>Moria,</hi> and here are taught to fetch, but not to carry; who will fetch fire from heaven not with <hi>Promethius,</hi> or a peaceable ſpirit, but with the ſons of Thunder, to conſume the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> and yet will <hi>carry no coals themſelves:</hi> which kind of creatures are derived (as ſome will have them) from the Greek fire — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the Brittiſh fire <hi>Tan,</hi> but they may as properly be deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is a Flint, which Flint is hard and cold, and yet on any colliſion or affront, will caſt forth fire, not only to burn the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans,</hi> but the <hi>Sanctuaryes</hi> of the good <hi>Samaritan,</hi> or as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>To burn up all the houſes of God in the Land:</hi> Such are ſome of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birams</hi> brood, who think that <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and all the lawful ſons of <hi>Levi</hi> do take too much upon them; ſuppoſing alſo, that any <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> is as fit to rule the day as <hi>Phoebus;</hi> yet—<hi>Finge datos currus quid aget</hi> — if he had the diſpoſing of it, what would he do? His Hiſtory will tell us — <hi>Non ſcit qua ſit iter</hi> — go he muſt, yet could not know which way to go: For when a <hi>Phaeton</hi> had —<hi>Jus &amp; moderamen aequorum</hi>— yea,—<hi>&amp; aquorum</hi>— the ruling of the unruly, and government of the giddy both by Sea and Land, what was then Right? the Anagram will tell you—<hi>Jus is vis,</hi> and <hi>vis</hi> is might, and might was right, and when might was right, he that was wiſe would take the advice of Chriſt, who bid him that had two Coats, ſell one and buy a Sword, or elſe he might chance to have nor Coat, nor Sword: For the Law of Nations was annihilated, our <hi>Magna Charta</hi> which was to maintain Monarchy, was cancelled— <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>— the Commons did command in chief,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 31.</note> the Prognoſticators propheſied lies, and as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>the people delighted to have it ſo:</hi> But if they looked to the end of the Verſe, they might have prevented
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:45328:18"/>the end thereof. Next, The Law of Nature, which was to nouriſh the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Branches both of the Olive, and of the Vine, was then neglected, and in their room — <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>foelix lolium &amp; ſteriles dominantur avaenae</hi> — the Wild Olive and the Sow-Thiſtle did ſway the Scepter. Thirdly,<note place="margin">Char. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Henere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Maria gina.</note> The Civil Law which was to ſupport the honour both of the Subject and Supreme, muſt not then defend the Court of honour, for fear that the Honourable of thoſe dayes ſhould be diſhonoured, and as it was wont to be ſaid — <hi>Mors Sceptra ligonibus aequat</hi>— Death only did ſhuffle Scepters and Shovels toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then the Shovels began to make themſelves equal with thoſe Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pters that then were, perceiving that there was no inequality in mens qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w could one be better than the other, when they were all alike? Fourthly, The <hi>Talick</hi> Law was quite laid by, for evil was repaied with good, and good with evil. Fifthly, The <hi>Salick</hi> Law, if any Law, was then in force. When as a <hi>Joanna</hi> was <hi>John,</hi> or an <hi>Aaron</hi> among the <hi>Romans,</hi> when <hi>Diana</hi> was —<hi>Dea,</hi> or a goddeſs among the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> when <hi>Delilae</hi> was <hi>Sampſon,</hi> or a Judge among the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> So the Maſculine gender in general, was leſs worthy than the Feminine in <hi>England.</hi> Laſt of all, That Law which at that time was Law, was not —<hi>Jus legis,</hi> but <hi>jus tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> — not the Law according to Law, but to the Times, which were law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and yet that Law was — <hi>In<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> diem</hi>—for no longer than a day, for what was Law this day, would the next day be out of date: In which times alſo, Valiant men were cow'd, and Cowards crowed on their dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hills: Learned men were ſilenced, and the illiterate had liberty to ſpeak any thing but what tended unto Loyalty; ſo that he was <hi>homo perpaucorum hominum,</hi> a man that muſt be found out by <hi>Diogenes</hi> his Lanthorn, and not by the light of the day, who had any humility or humanity in his dealing. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or ſelf-love was every where, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the love of Gods Servants, or of their own Souls, if it were any where, was <hi>Raraavis in terris,</hi> a rare Phaenix, which ſeldom of any man hath been ſeen, ſince as in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> time, ſo now we were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch as love to pleaſe our ſelves more than to pleaſe God. Nor let any one be ſo uncharitable as to think, that any man ſhould tripudeate or glory in this our ſhame—<hi>ſed pudeat</hi> ſhould be aſhamed that our glory ſhould be turned into ſhame. Nor ſhould we impute theſe our imperfections to any thing, but to Predictions and Propheſies which muſt be fulfilled. Firſt, To that of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith, that by reaſon of diſtractions and deſperate deſigns, <hi>In the laſt times there ſhall be dangerous dayes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.</note> the particulars whereof (that I may avoid all ſuſpition of ſpleen) I refer you to the Text. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, To that of the Pſalmiſt, where the froward affections of the Aged Creature, or <hi>Apolonius</hi> his old man regulating our actions, maketh too
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45328:19"/>many of the like condition, for it is ſaid of him — <hi>Jiblu abbad tacala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phim,</hi> be groweth old, aged, and decrepit, declining to corruption; who being alſo as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, ſubject unto vanity and violence, maketh man the object of them both by reaſon of his influence, in whom there is not only — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not hope, but a ſerious ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: who having alſo the knowledge of the voice (as <hi>Wiſdome</hi> ſpeaketh) doth know that the Spirit of God is as weary with wreſtling with mans fleſh as he was before the ſtood,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſd. 1.</note> ſo that not only the creature, but we muſt expect a fire before we can be refined, and therefore every good man ſhould be a <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſtand in the gap betwixt his brethren and Gods anger, that it might not proceed any farther; and though he be not ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous as to be blotted out of the book of life, as <hi>Moſes</hi> would have been for the ſafety of his brethren, yet he ſhould ſtand in the breach with that reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution that — <hi>Si fractus elabatur Orbis,</hi> ſhould the Axeltree of heaven break, and all the weight of the Wayne fall on him — <hi>Impavidum ferient ruinae,</hi> he ſhould not fear the fall thereof, hoping that mercy would fall down with it. Every man alſo ſhould be an <hi>Aaron—Duplices tendens ad ſidera palmas</hi> — holding his hands as an evening ſacrifice, and ſay — <hi>Parce pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r fulmenque tuum fera tela reconde, Spare thy people O Lord, spare thy people whom thou hast redeemed with thy most precious blood, and be not angry with us for ever,</hi> for, <hi>hinc ille lachrimae,</hi> here is our miſery, that what is amiſs will not be amended; it is ſo revealed unto us, <hi>He that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, will be unjuſt ſtill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>v. 22.11</note> 
               <hi>and he that will be filthy, will be filthy ſtill.</hi> This is an age not to alienate any thing from worſe to better, but from better to worſe. The ages fell from gold to ſilver, from ſilver to braſs, from braſs to iron, and from iron to ruſt. Our Swords which were turned into Mattocks, are turned into Swords again; our Spears which were turned into pruning-hooks, are, <hi>as they were.</hi> Our ſouls that by grace were made the veſſels of honour, are made by ſin the veſſels of diſhonour. Nor are here the <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> pillars of our impiety; Man will have a — <hi>Plus ultra,</hi> though he pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in his pride. The Bridge cannot confine our little <hi>Coricles,</hi> they will ſhoot the Bridge though thereby they ſink: Our greater veſſels cannot be kept within the compaſſe of the Line, they muſt ſhoot the Gulf, though they be never ſeen again. There was a great Gulf betwixt <hi>Abrahams</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and <hi>Dives</hi> his dark Dungeon, the paſſage through which <hi>Abraham</hi> in his navigation never could find out, but <hi>Dives</hi> did, or elſe he never had been, where God grant none of us may be— <hi>Gens, humana ruit per vetitum nefas. Man that hath taſted of the heavenly gift, and hath been partaker of Gods favors,</hi> will fall away from them ſo far, that he cannot be renued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain by repentance,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>br. 6.6.</note> not but that he might be pardoned if he could repent,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45328:19"/>but he ſhall not find grace to repent whereby he may be pardoned; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though graces are— <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, graces in their proper places, graces aſcending and deſcending. Yet no grace deſcendeth ſo low as to be found in ſuch a fall. And now for all this falling-ſickneſs is ſo fatal, and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious, yet few follow the advice of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which is, <hi>Let him that ſtandeth, take heed leſt he fall;</hi> and yet when he is falling, no man that loveth his own quietneſs will adviſe him to ſtand, for man is—<hi>Cereus in vitium flaecti moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus asper,</hi> as pliable as wax to leave any impreſſion of ſin on him, but to take off the impreſſion by perſwaſion, will be as hard, as to waſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the blood of ſome murder, which is done with ſo much difficulty, that though it be ſlubbered over, would appear, as the blood of many murders do until this day. Imperfections of nature are divers times ſo prevalent in the parents, that their children do fare the worſe for them; as when there is any deformity or crookedneſs in the father, it doth commonly come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the child, and there is no doubt but that a child may be like the father in condition as well as in proportion; and ſeldom alſo ſhall we ſee any ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh in the body, but there's ſome ill condition attending on it. <hi>Venus</hi> is ſaid to have a mole in her face, which mole did ſeeme to be a badge of beauty, but they that are skilled in phyſiognomy will tell you that it is a mark of ſome ill quality; for <hi>Mohal</hi> in Hebrew is — <hi>litura,</hi> or a blot that ſhould fall upon clean paper, and it is to be admired that any beauty ſhould make thoſe blots upon their faces by Art, which they have not by nature, unleſſe they would make wiſe men think worſe of them than they are. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, we daily ſee that deformities come unto fair features naturally want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Auxiliaries of Art for augmentation; If we will uſe Art, it ſhould be to prevent deformity and other misfortunes, and not to augment them. For our Criple may teach us that harms come to us ſooner than helps, who had been long diſeaſed, and yet had no man to help him, nor was likly ever to have, having ſuch an adjunct to his ache as may eaſily be imagined; for if his diſeaſe had been the <hi>Podagra,</hi> the <hi>Sciatica,</hi> or any lameneſſe that might come within the compaſs of <hi>Phyſick</hi> or <hi>Chirurgery,</hi> they would have killed or cured him within leſſe time than ſo many years as he lay lame. So that it is evident that he did—<hi>Magis paupertate quam paraliſi laborare</hi>— Suffer more by his poverty, than any other infirmity; and this will appear by a preſident of one that was ſick of the like, if not the ſame diſeaſe. He that was ſick of the Palſie, and not of poverty, had four men to attend on him, who carried him farder in his bed than the Text doth tell, and were ſo induſtrious, or rather audacious, that they did interrupt Chriſt in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and brake up the houſe upon him while he was preaching, which thou durſt not have done unleſſe they had been well paid for their pains,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:45328:20"/>which could not have been expected of a poor man. But before I proceed any farder, we may enquire why Chriſt ſhould ſuffer ſuch diſorder and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to be done to the houſe in which he was entertained, for the Text ſaith; That when they had broken up the roof of the houſe they let down the bed whereon the ſick of the Palſie lay. It is anſwered, that in thoſe hot Countreys their houſes were made with <hi>Peripats</hi> and walks on the tops of them, having decks inſtead of roofs, as they have in ſhips. So that the breaking up of the roof was but breaking of a lock at the moſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt perceiving that their faith was great, and their offence ſmall, gave them a — <hi>quietus eſt</hi> for the diſquieting the houſe, and a general ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittance of all dammages done, with a <hi>Noverint univerſi,</hi> that all men may know, that not only — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, theſe incivilities, but — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, all ſins whatſoever were forgiven, making good his word by a deed, ſaying, <hi>Take up thy Bed, and go to thy own houſe:</hi> And now that the houſe in which he was healed, was in the Form aforeſaid, ſhall appear by parciculars. Firſt, <hi>Histriones,</hi> or Mimick Actors perſonated whom they pleaſed on the tops of ſuch houſes. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Orators pleaded on them as our Lawyers do, according as they are paid. Thirdly, The Expounders of the Law, and ſuch Preachers as then were, preached unto their Auditories. — <hi>Vulgi ſtante Corona,</hi> All ſtanding, not one ſitting, unleſs he were a Senator, Suffragant, or ſome ſuch ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or perſon; and that preaching was in that manner, alſo is made plain in our Saviours words, ſaying, <hi>That which is spoken now in private, ſhall be preached on the houſe-tops.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. 10.7.</note> And now alſo when we ſhall gather up all the fragments and broken pieces together of what hath been ſaid, we ſhall find only this, That both were diſeaſed; the one rich, the other poor; one had friends, the other none, and that made him ſay, <hi>I have no man to help me.</hi> And how helpleſs man ſhall be that is poor, appeareth by a report of an Eccho anſwering to a voice in this manner — <hi>Si offeras pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam — uniam — at ſi non habeas — abeas</hi> — To him that hath it ſhall be given; but where nothing is, nothing can be expected: And it may be ſuppoſed that this Eccho formerly hath found the way even into <hi>Solomons</hi> Porch, or elſe why ſhould St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſay, when no man ſaid any thing to him, <hi>Silver and gold have I none.</hi> What hath been in <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> Porch we cannot promiſe, or what in St. <hi>Peters</hi> Porch, or in the houſe is, we cannot ſay, becauſe it hath been ſaid that there — <hi>Venalia ſunt omnia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Lamb <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſe,</hi> W. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nt.</note> — ſuch ſinnes are venial, but this we may ſay, That no ſuch thing is in the Porch of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> nor in the houſe, nor in the houſe of the Lamb, or concerning the Lamb of the houſe, nor in our <hi>Solomons</hi> Porch, or any thing reflecting upon the Perſon of <hi>Solomons</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:45328:20"/>For, he is not a receiver, but a giver — <hi>Nec dat quia abundat,</hi> nor doth he give out of his abundance, as they did which caſt into the Treaſury, but rather with the poor Widow, who giveth all that he hath, and more too: For it is well known, that he hath been fain to borrow the very gold, <hi>Thoſe outward and viſible ſigns of that inviſible grace which God hath given unto him,</hi> to give unto thoſe many thouſands of diſeaſed ſouls whom he hath cured. And it is to be wiſhed, that if ever <hi>Jove</hi> ſhould deſcend again in golden ſhowers into the lap of any one, it might be into his, who hath ſo bountifully beſtowed it, and where ſo great a bleſſing is given unto all thoſe on whom it is beſtowed: In which courſe of curing he followeth the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> or his Tutor <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who looketh not on the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or cauſe why one is ſick, but on the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, conſidering only that he is ſick. A Phyſitian may ſearch into the nature of the diſeaſe, that if it cometh by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or fulneſs, it may be cured by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, abſtinence or emptineſs, but if he enquire after the <hi>Pourquoy,</hi> or cauſe why he is ſick, that is <hi>Ultra Crepidam,</hi> beyond his <hi>Criſis</hi> or inquiſition. <hi>Socrates</hi> being blamed for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an Alms unto a wanderer, his anſwer was, <hi>I look upon his want, not on his wandering.</hi> When Chriſt cured <hi>Bartimeus</hi> of his blindneſs, he did not with the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> queſtion whether it came by original or actual ſin, but ſaid unto him, <hi>Receive thy ſight.</hi> It is true, that ſickneſs and diſeaſes are the ſequels of ſin; and that is the reaſon why our Saviour was never ſick, becauſe he could not ſin — <hi>Nil ille nec auſus</hi> — <hi>Nec potuit patrare nefas;</hi> and if his Omnipotency failed in any thing, it was becauſe he could not ſin, and yet it doth not follow, that the greateſt ſinners are moſt ſickly, for then Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians would have ſo many Patients, that it might well be ſaid — <hi>Dat Gale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus opes,</hi> let him that would be rich, be a Phyſician, for who would then be ſo rich and opulent as they? And now if you ſhould think it ſtrange that this our poor Creple ſhould lie eight and thirty years, and have no man to help him? It is anſwered, That he did not lie all that while at <hi>Betheſda,</hi> but that it hapned to him as unto the woman which had the bloody iſſue, who ſpent all that ſhe had among Phyſicians, as many have done, and are rather worſe than better: So that he made the Bath his —<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimum refugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> or laſt refuge to fly unto, and it was well for him that he had this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge: For as every diſeaſe is a Scurge, and every Scurge is — <hi>Plaga</hi>— or a Plague; ſo many have been ſcurged and plagued, and yet not ſo ſoon cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as this Creple was. Firſt, The <hi>Jews</hi> that dwelled in <hi>India,</hi> delighting in <hi>Mummi,</hi> or mans fleſh, becauſe they might not eat Swines fleſh, were plagued with the — <hi>Mark of the Beaſt,</hi> that — <hi>Lues veneria,</hi> or the <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rola,</hi> which Diſeaſe, though it were long before it came into our Land, yet it came to ſome purpoſe at the laſt. Secondly, The <hi>Philistines</hi> for being
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45328:21"/>too bold with the Ark of God, were plagued with Emralds and Mice in their hinder parts with a perpetual ſhame, ſo that not cured at all. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his family had ten plagues ſent unto them, for making <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> to attend on them, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n they ſhould have attended on their God, as here in brief:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Fit cruor ex undis conſpurcant omnia rana</l>
               <l>Dat pulvis ſiniphes, Poſtea muſca venit</l>
               <l>Dein pestis, poſt ulcera, grando, locuſta, tenebrae,</l>
               <l>Tandem Prototocos ultima plaga necat.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Firſt, Tears of compaſſion turned to bloody execution. Secondly, <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fones,</hi> venomous beaſts billited in the Kings Chambers. Thirdly, Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters, noyſome creatures creeping up and down in every corner. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Tarantula,</hi> the troubleſome Fly making men ſottiſh and mopiſh, and yet not enduting melody and harmony, the only means to help them. Fifthly, The Plague of <hi>Jeloſies,</hi> and fears frighting men and women out of that little wit they had. Sixthly, Blaines and blemiſhes upon the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of honeſt men, and botches and Buboes upon the beaſts that did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe them. Seventhly, Fire and hail, fiery Zeal and frozen Charity running together, grievous to behold. Eighthly, Locuſts, not Biſhops, Doctors and all learned men taking degrees in any Univerſity, as it is in the <hi>Geneva</hi> note, but <hi>Genevaiſts</hi> themſelves, who did eat up all the good in the Land. Ninthly, Darkneſs, Error, Ignorance, even in the <hi>Directories</hi> which ſhould lead unto the light. Laſt of all, No elder brother in any houſe which was not dead in duty either to Father or Mother, Nurſing or Natural. Theſe are the ten Plagues which were in <hi>Egypt,</hi> yea and in our <hi>Iſrael</hi> when it was <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> had the governing of it. All which were to teach us that God doth puniſh our offences with the Rod, and our ſins with Scurges, ſo that according to the quality of our ſin, there will be, as we may ſay, the quantity of our puniſhment. Firſt, Thoſe tranſgreſſions which are in — <hi>Tranſitu,</hi> or in paſſing to and fro, ſhall not have puniſhments anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thoſe that are in — <hi>Tentoriis,</hi> in the Tents of the ungodly. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, They that <hi>walk in the counſel of the wicked,</hi> who turn and return, as <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> going in to the Senate to come out again, are not ſo great offenders, as they that <hi>stand in the way of ſinners.</hi> Thirdly, Thoſe that ſtand in the way of ſinners are not ſo much to be blamed, as they that ſit and ſet up their reſt in the ſeat of Scorners, for the <hi>Chair-men</hi> deſerve the chiefeſt ſcurging. There was one Scurge, or one Plague more in <hi>Egypt,</hi> which hath not yet been mentioned: Thoſe — <hi>Urinatores,</hi> or divers under water, who, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſaith, <hi>be Gods wonders in the Deep,</hi> do find that there is one wave in the Sea, which is more dangerous and obnoxious to Mariners than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:45328:21"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:45328:22"/>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:45328:22"/>and it is thus deſcribed — <hi>Poſterior nono est, undecimo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> prior</hi> — it cometh after the ninth wave, and is before the eleventh, which muſt be the tenth, but the greateſt Plague in <hi>Egypt</hi> was neither the ninth, nor the tenth, but the eleventh — <hi>Quae venit haec peſtis peſtes ſupereminet omnes;</hi> for it comes like an After-reckoning, which vexeth one more than the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſum of all the particulars. And though — <hi>Decimation</hi> was the laſt of our <hi>Egyptian</hi> plagues while our <hi>Iſrael</hi> was <hi>Egypt,</hi> as is already ſaid; yet if that Plague by Providence had not been prevented from farther proceeding, there would have been nothing left to be Decimated, for we ſhould have been robbed or ſpoiled, as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> were, who making a Bridge of gold for their enemies to paſs over, left not a penny in their purſe; and not to trouble you with the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Text ſaith, <hi>They lent to Iſrael,</hi> — <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſos de plata, y vaſos de oro y veſtidos</hi> —not only their money, but their plate and their apparel, and ſo brought on themſelves the plague of Poverty, which was the plague Paramount of all plagues. When the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine was in <hi>Canaan,</hi> they had money in their Sacks to buy food in <hi>Egypt;</hi> but the Famine being in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and having no money, nor plate, nor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel to pawn, there would be cold comfort in coming to <hi>Canaan,</hi> or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any other Countrey. In this condition was this Creple, who being ſick of this poverty, ſhall neither, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, have kindred or acquaintance come near him, but ſtand afar off.<note place="margin">Pſa. 38.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> They ſee the Croſſe upon the door with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, but not a Croſſe within; they ſee the ſuperſcription over the Croſs, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Lord have mercy upon us;</hi> But if it were not for him, whoſe Superſcription <hi>Pilate</hi> ſet on his Croſſe, there would be no Lord, nor any other man to help them; and that which is worſt of all, when the Plague<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore breaketh, there is hope of recovery; but when this ſore breaketh, there is no recovery. This is that — <hi>Ingens telum,</hi> as the <hi>Adage</hi> termeth it, That breaketh not men, but battereth down Batteries, and with the help of hunger, breaketh through ſtone-walls: And although this is not alway true, That — <hi>Neceſſitas cogit ad turpia;</hi> Neceſſity ſhould make noble Spirits to conſpire with any ignoble actions; yet this is true, That — <hi>Dura ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtas Spiritus altos domans.</hi> — <hi>Inſuet a facere cogit.</hi> Neceſſity ſometime goeth beyond the bounds of Civility; and <hi>David</hi> when he was hungry, was more bold with <hi>Abiathars</hi> bread, than at another time he would have been; not that he intended — <hi>Sacra prophanis,</hi> That the Souldiers ſhould part Chriſts garments among them again, as it were; but foreſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that an inconvenience was better than a miſchief, gave unto them ſome of the conſecrated Cakes, that they might not be their own Carvers, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo, that where Souldiers are, ſomething muſt be had. <hi>Prevention,</hi> ſay the Polititians, <hi>is the principal point of Policy: And to meet a diſeaſe at the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:45328:23"/>door,</hi> ſay the Phyſitians, <hi>is the beſt way to keep him out of the houſe.</hi> Let ſome <hi>Remora,</hi> ſay the <hi>Oculiſts,</hi> ſtay the ruſhing of the rhumes, and we ſhall not need to cuppe the <hi>Catarrs,</hi> nor couch the <hi>Cataract.</hi> The beſt way to ſhun the Cockatrice, is to cruſh him in the ſhell. If a <hi>Baſilisk</hi> come to ſee, his eye may make a ſlaughter. <hi>And if thoſe Cockatrices Eggs had been hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, on which Sathan as the old Brood-Hen ſate ſo long, hoping to have brought a March brood.</hi> The taking of <hi>Abiathars</hi> bread, which was lawful only for the Prieſt to eat, would have been but a ſmall offence, for <hi>all the Children of God would have been eaten up, as if a man ſhould eat bread.</hi> But ſome will ſay—<hi>Caveat Ecclaeſia</hi>— This concerneth the Church, it ſhall never trouble us. It is confeſſed, and yet the Clergy may give this <hi>Caveat</hi> to the Laity — <hi>Jam tua res agitur paries cum proximus ardet</hi> — <hi>If the fire be kindled in Jacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 78.21</note>
               <hi>the flame will ſoone conſume Iſrael;</hi> and the Church and Common-wealth being one contignation, though there ſhould be a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wall betwixt them, yet if either bay of the building be on fire, the other hath reaſon for to fear. For, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>High and low, rich and poor, one with another will periſh altogether.</hi> Now ſince fire cannot diſtinguiſh betwixt man and man, every wiſe man ſhould ſtrive to extinguiſh the fire— <hi>Fax</hi> is a firebrand, from whence cometh Faction; and <hi>Tully</hi> can tell us, that—<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi eſt Fax, non eſt Pax,</hi> for ſaith he—<hi>Pax cum</hi> Antonio <hi>non eſt Pax, ſed pactio belli,</hi> which the Prophet doth Engliſh for us, <hi>There is no peace ſaith my God with the ungodly.</hi> There was a queſtion whether <hi>Faux</hi> the fire-man, or <hi>Fax</hi> the fire-brand was the greater offender — <hi>Exturbaſſe ſacrum conatus uterque ſenatum eſt,</hi> both undertaking to do that in few dayes, which the Devil had been five thouſand years deviſing. <hi>The one, by Sulphure to blow up the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;</hi> the other, <hi>by a Parliament to blow up the Scepter;</hi> and if we ſhall judge by the effect, the later was the worſe; for the fire of the former (God be praiſed) came to light before it came to light, but the fire of the later, hath like <hi>Etna,</hi> burned a long time, and God knoweth when it will be quenched; For ſome Salamanders who live by this fire, are as careful to keep it ſtill burning, being fomented by the ignobleſt of the people, as the Virgins of <hi>Veſta</hi> were to keep their fire, being founded by <hi>Numa Pompilius;</hi> which Salamanders alſo at their private fires do frame ſuch Tenents as ſhall adde fewel to their fire. Firſt, that a Parliament being choſen by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſhall not be diſſolved but by the conſent of the people, and ſo build a Caſtle in the air, caſting away the Corner-ſtone of the building; for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the people, can make no building without <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is the foundation; and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the King, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the foundation or eſtabliſhment of the people. But <hi>Cinthius aurem vellit.</hi> Divines in taking their degrees, are admitted to read St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and not <hi>Machiavel,</hi> therefore to keep my ſelf
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:45328:23"/>within compaſſe, and conſine my diſcourſe to the method of — <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od medicorum est,</hi> this I may ſafely ſay, Firſt, St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith that we are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or called before we are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or choſen. Next, our Saviours rule is, that there muſt be a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, before <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a power given to act, before we can make any Acts. Laſt of all the Univerſi y teacheth, That— <hi>Ejus eſt ſegregare, cujus eſt congregare;</hi> that he who hath power to call a Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, hath alſo power to diſcontinue it, or diſſolve it at his pleaſure; and we have at this time a holy Convocation, and a royal Prieſthood; whom — <hi>Non vox populi, ſed vox Dei Convocavit,</hi> the King hath called, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hath choſen, but God gave the word, and great and gracious was the company which were called and choſen. They need not trouble themſelves about the point who ſhall diſſolve them, for they proceeding in that peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able way as they hitherto have done, may ſit till no one will be weary of their ſitting, except themſelves; and when they are weary, we wiſh that they may — <hi>Geminaſque reſumere vires,</hi> go into the Countrey, take breath, and to it again, ſince to our comfort this is the, courſe they take. Firſt, They do — <hi>Diſſuere,</hi> not <hi>Diſrumpere,</hi> unſtich the ſeams of Schiſm and Diſſention, and not tear in pieces all at once. Secondly, As good Phyſitians knowing that there is—<hi>Pleura pura,</hi> as impute a Pluriſie of pure blood, as well as overplus of groſs and impure blood, and therefore will let out that blood which will weaken the Body, and cheriſh all ſuch blood as will ſtrengthen it. Thirdly, They remember that the Sun with his bright beams did get away the Countrey <hi>Coleincloutes</hi> Cloke, when <hi>Boreas</hi> with his bluſtering was glad to go without it. This is the way in which they walk, and therefore all that love the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the proſperity of <hi>Zion,</hi> will ſay,— <hi>Ite bonis avibus,</hi> Ride on and proſper, and we will wiſh you good luck in the Name of the Lord. And though —<hi>Crambe his poſita mors eſt</hi>— that a ſecond Seſſions may ſeem as death to thoſe that deſerve it, yet— <hi>Decies repetita placebunt,</hi> the oftner Your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journings and returnings ſhall be, the more delightful they will be to thoſe that are Deſerving: The next Tenent of theſe <hi>Salamanders,</hi> is, That the Sheep ſhall ſheet the Shepherds, and yet the Shepherds ſhall have no ſhare with the Sheep; and although it be the part of a good Shepherd to ſheer his Sheep, and not to clip them, yet they will not only clip them, but ſheer them ſo cloſe, that in the coldeſt weather and Winter of adverſity, they ſhall have no warmth of their own wooll. But they do as their ſheers do teach them, who as plainly as they c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ſpeak, cry <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Clepte,</hi> not only ſteal, ſteal, but teach them Sacriledge, the greateſt Theft of all. Now leaſt ſuch diſturbers of the Times ſhould find better enrertainment in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered affections, than thoſe that tend unto tranquility, Chriſt in his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:45328:24"/>own language ſaith, — <hi>Alta amenu, Say not Amen to them, or believe them not.</hi> And not only ſo, but in his Goſpel bids us beware of them; and though the <hi>Hebrew, Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Texts ſay only, <hi>Beware of men;</hi> yet the <hi>French, Spaniſh,</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> Texts do all ſay, <hi>Guard your ſelves from them:</hi> And the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſaith plainly, <hi>Shut your doors againſt them.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo adviſeth us, <hi>To have nothing to do with them;</hi> and telleth <hi>Timothy,</hi> That they are deceivers, and at laſt will be deceived; who gadding betwixt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which is built at unity within it ſelf, and <hi>Jericho</hi> a City ſubject to Lunacy, as its name importeth, will find in the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> his Coſmography, that there is a dangerous Deſert betwixt them, diſaſterous unto Paſſengers; for there <hi>Zedechia</hi> loſt his Army, being all taken Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; there he loſt his ſons, being ſlain before his face; there he loſt his eyes, all being diſpitefully done by <hi>Nebuchadnezer.</hi> There alſo St. <hi>Lukes</hi> Paſſenger loſt all that he had: being wounded, and left half dead; and all that paſs that way, may fear, leſt they fare as the other did; for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Truth will ſtrip off their Jeſuitical long Robes, and leave them naked, then — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, their own Recorder calling to mind their many Conſederacies, will give them their firſt wound, then — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Conſultation, Inquiſition, Election and Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Practice, will, like <hi>Caeſars</hi> Senators, wound them all at once, and leave them in deſpair, as bad as dead. And as a Deer, once wounded, all the Herd will forſake him; ſo their <hi>Levites</hi> may look on them, but leave them, and let them lie. Their <hi>Prieſts</hi> may look on them too, and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture pity them, but will paſs by them; ſo that— <hi>Miſeretur aliquis ſuccurrit nemo.</hi> Some man may pity them, but there will be no man to help them: Since then — <hi>Frigeſcit charitas foris, caleſcat domi:</hi> Since, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>No man careth for my ſoul,</hi> let every man be more careful of his own ſoul; and whatever our Acts are, let us look unto our <hi>Exits,</hi> for we ſhall come from this earthly Stage with a — <hi>Plaudite,</hi> an Applauſe, or with ſuch a — <hi>Sibile,</hi> as ſhall hiſs us off from the Stage. Let us not then with a — <hi>Cras moriemini,</hi> or careleſs courſe of life, ſay with <hi>Heſter, If I periſh, I periſh;</hi> for we deal not with man, as <hi>Heſter</hi> did, but with an <hi>Emanuel,</hi> and with him there is mercy; in the mean while, the Moraliſt will tell us, that— <hi>Suae quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> faber est fortunae,</hi> fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling will frame a good Fortune, but Fate and Deſtiny have nothing to do with Divinity; for then with God there would be no — <hi>Anthropopathy,</hi> or relenting on mans repenting: but <hi>Ninevi</hi> will deny that, and <hi>David</hi> will affirm, That as man feareth, ſo is Gods pleaſure or diſpleaſure; nay, God is ſo pitiful,<note place="margin">96.</note> that upon mans Petitions he will rather pleaſe him than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; yea, and ſo merciful, that man ſhall have his own will, though it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:45328:24"/>Gods own Will: Nay, God was fain to petition <hi>Moſes</hi> that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf might be at quiet, ſaying, <hi>Let me alone;</hi> ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Ex. 32.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and promiſed to make him a great man, and what could he have more? but <hi>Moſes</hi> would not let him alone, nor have his will, but made him alter his Will, and reverſe his Order, and delivered <hi>Iſrael</hi> from deſtruction when God had fully determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and reſolved to deſtroy it; and the Poet, as if he had ſeen the paſſage betwixt God and <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaith thus,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Saepe <hi>Jovem</hi> vidi, cum jam ſua mittere vellet</l>
               <l>Fulmina, thure d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>to ſustinuiſſe manum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>I have not ſeen <hi>Jove</hi> (as he might ſay) but <hi>Jeh va</hi> to be overpowered by Prayer, ſince man may not only— <hi>Perorare</hi>—obtain by intreaty, but— <hi>Prece cogere</hi>— compel God, as it were, to be pitiful, for when <hi>Phinehas</hi> ſtood up,<note place="margin">Pſ. 106.3</note> and prayed, the plague ceaſed: And now, as Deſtiny hath nothing to do with Divinity, ſo neither with Eternity, for it is confined to Mortality; — <hi>Statutum eſt</hi>—it is Decreed, that we muſt all die, and that we muſt all come to judgement; but it is not Decreed, that any man ſhall be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before he come to judgement; and <hi>Feſtus</hi> told <hi>Agrippa,</hi> that it was an unreaſonable thing, that <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould be condemned before his Caſe was heard; and how much more is it an unreaſonable thing, that any man ſhall be condemned before he come to the Tribunal Seat of juſtice! A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, If there were any condemnation before judgement, to what end ſhould Chriſt come to judgement? Firſt, The ſouls of the righteous are in the hands of God, and no torment ſhall touch them; and why ſhould they come? Secondly, The ſouls which are predeſtinated to condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are condemned already, and what ſhould they do there? So that as the King was fain to bring in High-way-men, and ſuch as lay under hedges, to furniſh his Table at the Wedding: So when Chriſt ſhall come to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he muſt alſo ſeek out ſuch as are in the old — <hi>Limboes,</hi> or in the aerial — <hi>Ergaſtulaes</hi> to fetch out the — <hi>Ixioniſts</hi> from their wheels, and the <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lides</hi> from their bottomleſs buckets, to be in a — <hi>Parado,</hi> or readineſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the general Appearance, and conſequently, Predeſtination will be the principle Argument to prove that Third place wherewith the <hi>Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narij</hi> are ſo much off nded. But a day of Dome there muſt be; <hi>the place,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, is prepared already</hi>— Dome is a Saxon word, and not Doom, and ſo is Home; both ſhewing that we muſt all go to our— <hi>Ultimum do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum,</hi> to our laſt, and our long home: Which Dome in the Anagram, or in the ſame letters is Mode, and according to the Mode and manner of our living ſhall be our Dome, and not according to our Deſtiny, but our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert. <hi>Abraham,</hi> for the prevention of deſtruction, or coming to the place of <hi>Torment,</hi> as <hi>Dives</hi> did term it, did not refer <hi>Dives</hi> his brethren to the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:45328:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:45328:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:45328:26"/>
               <hi>Meds</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> with whom no perſwaſion could make alteration, but to <hi>Moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> and the Prophets, who teach, <hi>That by amendment there may be atonem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt.</hi> At which day of Dome alſo the Books will be opened, both of our Delinquences, and our Acquittances. Our Delinquences will be—<hi>in numero,</hi> many?—<hi>in pondere,</hi> heavy; Our Acquittances will be few, and ſcarſe as many as—<hi>Thebarum portae vel Divitis oſtea Nili;</hi> yea, and ſo few, that a poor man may number them without a Cypher, if they be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to our payment, either of our <hi>vows</hi> unto God, or <hi>promiſes</hi> unto man. In like manner, when the Books are opened, the Balances will be brought, where our ill actions will overpoſe our good; and though Mercy may help in holding the Scales, yet <hi>Abraham</hi> told the Judge unto his face, That he which doth hold the Balance, muſt be juſt. So then —<hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rditio tua dete,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18.15</note>
               <hi>O Iſrael,</hi> God did as much unto his Vineyard as he could do, and was ſorry that the Vineyard was not ſenſible of it; wherefore the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, and the Husbandmen of the Vineyard, may drink the wine or the dregs thereof as they pleaſe: For it is not in the Text, <hi>Faeces quas expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerit hibent impij;</hi> God did not ſqueeſe out the dregs for the ungodly of the earth to drink;<note place="margin">Pſ 75.8.</note> but it is — <hi>Faeces quas expreſſerint,</hi> The ungodly did wring them out themſelves for themſelves to drink, as ſaith <hi>Pagnine,</hi> and all the three Engliſh Tranſlators: So that ſtill our Dome will be no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than as we do; and <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his — <hi>Quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vult,</hi> ſaith, That who ever will be ſaved, muſt believe it; and <hi>Enoch</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Jude,</hi> Propheſied to the ſame purpoſe; and all that were before <hi>Enoch,</hi> ſet their names unto a Propheſie to confirm it, as you may read,— <hi>ADAM</hi> man, <hi>SETH</hi> being put, <hi>ENOSH</hi> into a deſperate condition,<note place="margin">Chr. 1.1</note>
               <hi>KENAN</hi> by his own occaſion <hi>MAHALALEEL,</hi> the light of God, <hi>JERED</hi> did deſcend from heaven, <hi>ENOCH</hi> teaching us, <hi>METH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SELAH,</hi> That by his death he would ſend <hi>LAMECH,</hi> to the humble and afflicted, <hi>NOAH</hi> reſt and peace, <hi>SHEM</hi> and impoſe, <hi>HAM</hi> his high diſpleaſure, <hi>JAPHETH</hi> to thoſe that were haughty and high-minded. Theſe Predictions ſhould prepare us for our appearance, and to conſider again that — <hi>Nemo laeditur niſi à ſeipſo,</hi> our ſorrows and our ſufferings are from our ſelves. God made nor ſin, nor death, nor would that any one ſhould die,<note place="margin">Viſ. 1.</note> we have his Word for it, we have his Oath for it, and Cautions that we ſhould nor ſin, nor die — <hi>Nolite zelare mortem, Seek not death in the error of your life, and pull not down deſtruction upon your own heads with the works of your own hands.</hi> St. <hi>Jerom</hi> ſaith, that this Creple was ſo long lame, becauſe he had been long a ſinner, and that Chriſt could not cure him of his ſickneſs, until he had cleanſed him of his ſin: It is ſo in the body natural, firſt take away the cauſe, and then come unto the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:45328:26"/>cure. It is ſo in the body ſpiritual, firſt — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> caſt out foul ſpirits, then — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, heal all diſeaſes. It is ſo in the body Political. There muſt be a caſting out, before there can be a curing: It was ſo in healing this poor Creple — <hi>Chriſtus tollit peccatum, claudus tollit grabbatum,</hi> Chriſt taketh off the ſin, the Creple taketh up his Couch. And now whither (Morally) muſt he go? —<hi>In domum ſuam, non alienum;</hi> into the houſe of ſtrangers he muſt not go, we have a Home to go unto, though it be home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and it is our ſhame that it is ſo homely that no man careth to come to us: There are houſes more neatly garniſhed, but conſider what ſpirits come unto them, we ſhall not want hunting to be brought into their Toyles, but when the Hunter hath caught us,—<hi>Capta relinquit,</hi> he will not care for us. It was ſo with the Paſſenger, he had no man to help him: It was ſo with this poor Creple, he had no man to help him: It will be ſo with us all, if we want help. There will be no man to help us, but our <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel,</hi> who is both God and man, Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>Cui gloria.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
